<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new survey of the Turkish empire and government in a brief history deduced to this present time, and the reign of the now Grand Seignior, Mahomet the IV, the present and XIV emperor : with their laws, religion, and customs : as also an account of the siege of Newhausel.</title>
            <author>Marsh, Henry, fl. 1663-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 193 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52021</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M729A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15790</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13147389</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13147389</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98077</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52021)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98077)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 428:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new survey of the Turkish empire and government in a brief history deduced to this present time, and the reign of the now Grand Seignior, Mahomet the IV, the present and XIV emperor : with their laws, religion, and customs : as also an account of the siege of Newhausel.</title>
                  <author>Marsh, Henry, fl. 1663-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 76, 108 p., [2] leaves of plates : ill., port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Marsh ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Epistle dedicatory" signed: H. Marsh.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [8].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Austro-Turkish War, 1661-1664.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  History --  1453-1683.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  History --  Mehmed IV, 1648-1687.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  Social life and customs.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:98077:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <figure>
                  <head>The true and Exact Portrayture of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> MAHOMET y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>: fourteenth
Emper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the Turks now raigning in 1663</head>
                  <byline>MatthAei, Florentinus Pinxit:</byline>
                  <byline>Io: Chantry ſculp:</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98077:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A New Survey OF THE Turkish Empire AND GOVERNMENT, IN A Brief
HISTORY deduced to this preſent Time, and the Reign of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he now GRAND SEIGNIOR
<hi>MAHOMET</hi> the IV. The preſent and XIV. Emperor. With their Laws,
Religion and Cuſtoms. As alſo an Account of the Siege of NEWHAUSEL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Marſh</hi> at the ſign
of the Princes Arms in <hi>Chancery-Lane.</hi> 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98077:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98077:2"/>
            <head>To the Right VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful, Sir AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DREW RICCARD, Knight, and
Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the <hi>Levant</hi> Company.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Turkiſh Breviary and Abſtract, as of right and due
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſeth it ſelf to your <hi>Hands,</hi> in which the
<hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:98077:3"/>of our Intelligence and Commerce with
that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is very worthily and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently <hi>placed.</hi> Be pleaſed
therefore among other leſſer <hi>Concerns</hi> of your
<hi>Surinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> therein, to ſuffer your <hi>Name</hi> to be
<hi>intereſted</hi> in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage of this Brief <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RVEY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prefixing whereof was partly deſigned to <hi>compoſe</hi>
and <hi>civilize</hi> thoſe <hi>horrid</hi> and <hi>dire conceptions</hi> we
have of thoſe Barbarous Arms; by letting the World ſee, that perſons of
the greateſt Humanity have and do maintain a conſtant and amicable
Coreſpondence with them; partly to let their preſent <hi>Dread</hi> and
<hi>Puiſſance</hi> do ſervice to thoſe <hi>fair</hi> and <hi>obliging
atractions</hi> for which your <hi>Name</hi> is no leſs Famous,<pb facs="tcp:98077:3"/>and partly to <hi>vindicate</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> of the
<hi>Diſcourſe</hi> enſuing, when we offer it at ſo <hi>known</hi> an
<hi>Altar,</hi> and to ſo <hi>competent</hi> a <hi>Judge</hi> and
<hi>Patron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that advantage with your own <hi>Eminence</hi> will juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
engage an <hi>Ambition</hi> to <hi>ſound</hi> your <hi>Name</hi> in the
gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Voyce</hi> and <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> of the World, which is now
bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied with this <hi>Mighty Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch;</hi> whoſe <hi>Glories</hi> and
<hi>Succeſſes</hi> will have this further <hi>felicity,</hi> that they have
<hi>harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly</hi> reached us, under your particular
<hi>Protection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And under that let the World alſo be taught, the great and
admirable effects of <hi>Sobriety</hi> and <hi>Abſtinence,</hi> and the
miſchiefs of Ryot and Exceſs: For this <hi>Aſian</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:98077:4"/>People,
once the nauſeated and baſeſt dregs of the World, odious for their
Luxury, and Infamous for their Slavery, (the neceſſary conſequents
thereof) are now by their temperance and abſtemiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, (the injunction
and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of an abſurd Religion) become the Mightieſt Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and
greateſt Lord of the Univerſe: and by irreſiſtible and over bearing
approaches, have given the Empire of <hi>Germany</hi> (the <hi>reeling,
ſtagger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Remnant of the Fourth Monarchy a <hi>Cup of
Trembling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God in his good time heal thoſe Breaches, and pardon the many
provoking ſins of Chriſtendom, and continue us in our undeſerved peace, 
<pb facs="tcp:98077:4"/>and your Noble Self and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily therein, in all Honour and
proſperity.</p>
            <closer>So prays 
<signed>Your Humble and Devoted Servant <hi>H.
Marſh.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:98077:5"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>THe Reader is deſired to mend and obſerve a miſtake; in Page
8. Line 25 for 1633. read 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98077:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hile the noyſe of thoſe barbarous Armies, that now prevail
in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly threaten the adjacent Hereditary
Dominions of the <hi>German</hi> Emperour, as Arch-Duke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi>
do reſound through the whole Chriſtian world; which<pb facs="tcp:98077:6"/>may juſtly
fear the ſecond part of that Tragedy, which the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>undation of the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals</hi>
terribly effected in thoſe parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> that now are the next
affrighted Neighbours to this Invaſion; It will be a ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
endeavour, I preſume, to give ſome account of this terrible Enemy; whoſe
diſtant efforts give us the ſecure and quiet contemplation of his
ſtrength and power, while it employs other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of Chriſtendom in
haſty and tumultuous Action, and hath hurled them into a general
diſtraction and conſternation.</p>
            <p>I will not be curious to dive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this providence and grand
Affair of the world, unto which ſo many ſtrange events ſeem to be
chained, as that the Fate of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe is judged by ſome to be
concerned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; but he that ſhall conſider and peruſe ſome modern
Treatiſes which hint at this very thing, and ſhall likewiſe weigh with
himſelf thoſe great mutations and changes which have been wrought in this
Kingdom,<pb facs="tcp:98077:6"/>eſpecially the late bleſſed Reſtitution, muſt
beleive that ſome extraordinary Revolution is at hand, and that ours, and the
like in other parts, are but the precurſory and predictory ſigns of ſome
Concluſive wonder.</p>
            <p>The expectation of the world hath long laboured under the
diſcourſe and diſputes about Antichriſt, variouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceived by a
multitude of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as alſo about the period of the Roman Empire, which
now is viſible only, and hath been ſo for ſome ages in the Houſe of
<hi>Auſtria,</hi> ſupported by the Grandeur of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi>
Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy: and it is now no vain and groundleſs an opinion of the ſame that
one or both of theſe Myſterious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues in humane judgement will in this
preſent juncture be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, at leaſt ſome greater light be given by
this claſhing and colliſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Eaſtern and Weſtern Princes the
ſucceſs whereof will decide whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Caeſar aut Nullus,</hi> a
Caeſar or No Body.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98077:7"/>The Reader therefore I hope will take in good part
this brief Account of the Cuſtoms, Laws and manners (ſubjoyned to this
brief Hiſtory of this Formidable Nation) as they are deſcribed by a worthy
hand, a perſon of quality und experience.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98077:7"/>
            <head>A NEW SURVEY OF THE Turkiſh Empire.</head>
            <head type="sub">PART. I.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Riſe of the Turkiſh Empire, and its
Preſent Greatneſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Puiſſant, and almoſt numberleſs people, in their
Armies and Hoſts, which like <hi>Xerxes</hi> his Forces, drink whole Rivers
dry as they march, came from moſt contemptible and petty<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98077:8"/>Originals; and like the Roman Empire, which began from a col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected
rabble of looſe and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawed perſons, was founded in a Company of theiving
Shepheards, who wandring up and down like a running diſeaſe, infeſted and
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted all places they came to, and at laſt grew to ſuch
conſiderable ſtrength, like a Snow-ball, that they became ſuſpect to
the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> both Pagan and Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The riſe of the Turk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh power.</note>The
firſt appearance which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred them Famous and Notable to the world, was
under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and leading of their Captain <hi>Tangrolipix,</hi> who was
called in by the King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> to ayd him againſt the potent and
prevailing Armies of the <hi>Saracens,</hi> which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving readily undertaken,
and ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly and ſuccesfully atcheived; this Auxiliary took
occaſion to carve for himſelf, and erect a new Principality and Empire, as
well as upon his friends, whom he pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98077:8"/>to reſcue, as
upon their common enemies territory, making both of them the equal prey of his
ambition of Soveraignty and Dominion.</p>
               <p>This new Family continued in this Uſurpation and Intruſion
with various ſucceſs one hundred and ſeventy years, to the year of our
Lord, 1300. But ſtanding ſolely upon its own legs, neither ſtrengthned
nor ſecured by any al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liances, and waſted with a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual War with the
former juſt Propietors of the Land they had treacherouſly and forcibly
wreſted, it expired its dying, gaſping breath into a younger ſlip of the
ſame Houſe, for now the <hi>Zelzuccian</hi> Name and Fortune was
tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Oguzian</hi> Tribe (which were the two, and onely
Deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants of this people) whom Fate had adopted to the reſerve and
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of her greateſt and benigneſt Favours, which ſhe decreed to
double upon it; for having made an eſſay of the formers aptneſs to 
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98077:9"/>glory, and laid the dead colours in it, of a Majeſtical and
Auguſt Form and Feature; drew it perfect afterwards in this beautiful and
fair proportion, in which we now ſee the Turkiſh Empire.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The riſe of the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note>The Infant Darling of this riſing greatneſs, was the famous
<hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> to whom the grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors refer, and ambitiouſly
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title their Sir-name, who having precariouſly obtained a ſmall quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity
of ground from his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, upon proteſtation of his quiet and peaceable
demeanour, partly by courage, and partly by treachery, over-ran the whole
Country of <hi>Bythynia,</hi> in the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer <hi>Aſia;</hi> and dying,
left the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of enlarging and extending his Dominions to his Son and
Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor <hi>Orchanes,</hi> whoſe Sons im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe Fortune, like the
<hi>Colloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> beſtrid the Helleſpont, and conveyed the Turkiſh
Enſigns into Europe, whoſe delicious and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſoil, ſo pleaſed
andentic ed<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98077:9"/>thoſe Conquerours, that the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Seat was
firſt fixed here at <hi>Adrianople,</hi> to which moſt of the vicine
Princes were forced to come and pay tribute and homage: ſuch was the
ſlaviſh condition of <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via</hi> and <hi>Bulgaria,</hi> and moſt
part of <hi>Slavonia,</hi> afterwards ſwallowed up in abſolute
Mahumetaniſm, and made Provinces of this monſtrous Seignory.</p>
               <p>But that which conſtituted, and was as the formal being
thereof, was the Conqueſt and Poſſeſſion of
<hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> now called <hi>Stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boli,</hi> the Magnificent
Throne of the Eaſtern Empire, which reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned its glories to victorious
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet, <hi>May</hi> 29. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1450. and transferred its
imperial Title to that Regal claym, his Anceſtors had enjoyed. This
irrecoverable loſs, and lop of one of the greateſt and chiefeſt members
of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſo ſtunned the Greeks, and other petty Princes, who yet
maintained their Dominions, that<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98077:10"/>moſt of them were either
ſuddenly reduced, or tamely yeilded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which was the fate of the
<hi>Epirots</hi> (though they held out for a while, by the unexampled con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct
and felicity of <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi>) the <hi>Rhodians,</hi> the
<hi>Cypriots,</hi> and Iſles of the <hi>Mediteranean</hi> Sea, and laſtly,
in the Reign of <hi>Solyman,</hi> of <hi>Moldavia, Valachia,</hi> part of
<hi>Tranſilvania</hi> and <hi>Hungaria,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he peirced and
paſſed as far as <hi>Vienna,</hi> (and beyond it, in other part, of
<hi>Auſtria</hi>) which by the fear of his approach, ſaw her Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burbs, and
Houſes, and Gardens of pleaſure fired and ruined, that he might have no
ſhelter for his men, when he ſhould attempt the ſiege, which he did, but
in vain: but ſuch was his importunate ambition of effecting a total
conqueſt of that Country, in which he had been partly ſuccesful to the
gayning of the better half of that Kingdom of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> and ſeizing
<hi>Buda</hi> the Capital City thereof, that he<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98077:10"/>made
ſeveral expeditions in perſon, even in his old Age, and dyed at his return
from taking <hi>Zigeth,</hi> though gallantly defended to the laſt man, by
Count <hi>Serinus,</hi> great Anceſtor to the Emperors Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſſimo,
now in that Kingdom. Not to mention the Augmentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Empire, by the
trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal acceſſions of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter parts of
<hi>Aſia</hi> the Great, both Nations of the ſame Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The death of <hi>Soly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
                  </note>From
the time of this <hi>Solymans</hi> Deceaſe, about 1566. till now, little or
no attempts were made this way by his Succeſſors, for <hi>Amurath</hi> his
Son, <hi>Mahomet</hi> and <hi>Achmat,</hi> were Princes given to quiet, and
Home Delights, ſo that moſt men conjectured, this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire was at its Zenith
and Solſtice, and full ſtop, and would decline as faſt as it roſe; and
that glory wearied with ſuch a train of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, would flag at laſt,
if not be pulled back again with the weight<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98077:11"/>of them, and
cruſh it to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The death of <hi>Achmat</hi> the
firſt.</note>And this was almoſt concluded on, when after the death of
<hi>Achmat,</hi> there immediately fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ſuch Convulſions in that
State, and recedings from thoſe obſerved rules of policy, which were the
ſecurity of its Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſaving the lives of
the younger brethren of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, as <hi>Achmat</hi> did by
<hi>Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha,</hi> and he by <hi>Achmats</hi> three Sons; <hi>Oſman,</hi>
who at tweelve years of age had the Government tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to him from his
Uncle <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha,</hi> and was afterſtrangled by the tumultuary
<hi>Janizaries, Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rath</hi> or <hi>Morat,</hi> and <hi>Ibrahim</hi> (the
Father of the preſent Emperour) who all reigned ſucceſſively; of which
three, <hi>Morat</hi> proved a moſt Heroique Prince, and of as great if not
greater ſpirit then any of his Progenitors. He dyed in 1633. at the ſiege
of <hi>Bagdat,</hi> alias <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon,</hi> (whether he had deſigned 
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98077:11"/>the <hi>Janizaries</hi> for ſlaughter and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation, as
being the cauſes and Agents of all thoſe troubles and diſloyalties which
had happened to his Brother and Uncle, intending in their room to erect a new
kind of ſtanding Militia, which ſhould be more abſolutely at his command.
Being asked upon his death-bed, occaſioned by a violent Fever (in the ſaid
year 1640.) whom he would appoint to ſucceed him, he diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and
angrily replied, <hi>Will there be any more worlds when I am dead?</hi> He was
thought to have favoured the Chriſtians for his Mothers ſake, and therefore
choſe this expedition againſt the <hi>Perſian.</hi> His immature fate was
much lamented by his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, for his juſtice and temperance, and care of
them; but welcomed by the <hi>Janizaries,</hi> who began to perceive his drift
againſt them, and who notwithſtanding ſaluted his Brother
<hi>Ibrahim</hi> with the Imperial dignity the year aboveſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98077:12"/>
                  <hi>Ibrahim</hi> immediately upon his
Aſſumption renewed the League with the Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> which
had been concluded by <hi>Ach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat</hi> in 1612. and had been thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto
punctually and inviolably obſerved: but the Galleys of <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi>
meeting with his wealth, coming from <hi>Cairo</hi> and <hi>Alexandria,</hi>
and carrying them, and one of his dear <hi>Sultana's,</hi> which was on board,
away for that Iſland, put him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a rage, that without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
reſtitution he vow'd to attaque Chriſtendom: Which immediately he commenced
againſt the <hi>Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> as abettors, if not complices in the fact,
upon whoſe Trade and Territories he might wreak his fury, which would be
ſpent in vain againſt that impregnable Iſle, which had blemiſhed the
proweſs and glory of his Anceſtors: and having rigged a Fleet, and raiſed
an Army, he ſet upon the Iſle of <hi>Candy</hi> by Sea, and by Land up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<hi>Dalmatia,</hi> reſolved againſt any<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98077:12"/>agreement or
accommodation ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, and with various fortune maintained the War, till the
<hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> tumulting again, depoſed him, and ſet up his Son
<hi>Mahomet</hi> the Fourth, a ſtripling, and whom they might govern as they
pleaſed. He died in the ſaid fatal year 1648. the murderous Revolution of
Princes; but how, is not certain: For ſuch is the knack of this Tyranny, that
the world cannot tell, whether the Prince or his Slaves do die the
faireſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98077:13"/>
               <head>Of the preſent Reign of <hi>Sultan Mahomet</hi> the
Fourth:</head>
               <p>SUltan <hi>Ibrahim</hi> being thus depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, his Eldeſt Son
<hi>Mahomet</hi> was with general applauſe ſaluted Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and his
Mother the <hi>Sulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> was highly complemented: His Name did much
conciliate the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the people for his great Grand-fathers ſake,
<hi>Mahomet</hi> the Third, whoſe memory was highly honoured and beloved, and
becauſe of his comelineſs of Feature, and towardlineſs of Mind, which
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed the revival of all his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors vertues in himſelf.</p>
               <p>There had been frequent changes by death, and diſgrace of the
Prime <hi>Viſiers</hi> in the next preceding Reigns: It is a Dignity far
great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then our Lord Chancellour, for he commands ſupremely both in 
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98077:13"/>peace and war, at home and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, but of ſuch ſhort
and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain poſſeſſion, eſpecially of late, that the Turks have a
Proverb, <hi>The greateſt Perſons and Officers in that government, are but
at beſt fair ſtatues of Glaſs.</hi> He that admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred this place at
the Emperors Aſſumption, was an old States-man and a perſon of good
ſucceſs and conduct, and of as good age and experience, and who
queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſs layd thoſe Noble principles and elements of glory and
ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this young Monarch, which the Chriſtian world now ſadly feels.
For from that diſreputation, and deſpicableneſs of the Turkiſh power,
by reaſon of thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions and inteſtine troubles, which for ſome
years before had beſotted, and as was hoped, had emaſculated the Policy,
Prudence, Valour, and Courage of that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; he at the firſt inſtant of
his Government gave manifeſt ſignes of a Mercurial and Martial
Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98077:14"/>and with his own active <hi>Genius,</hi>
(the example of Princes being the great Engine of worth) ſoon buoyed up the
Spirits of his people to their former pitch of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiude, and bravery of mind,
awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened and reſtored their loſt diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline: and to whet their new
furbiſhed Scimitars, reſolved to employ them altogether againſt the
Chriſtians, upon the irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable quarrel of Religion, the great Incentive
to Heroical enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, eſpecially amonſt the Turks, where <hi>zeal
always fights half the Battel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this purpoſe he reſolved to proſecute the War againſt
the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians,</hi> which his Father had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnn, and though at his firſt
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance upon it, Fortune ſeemed to oppoſe his deſigns, and ſeverely
to exerciſe his glorious and aſpiring mind, with a very great defeat given
his naval Forces by the Sea, the greateſt ever given them ſince
<hi>Lepanto</hi> fight, wherein he loſt<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98077:14"/>forty eight
Gallies, 6 Galiaſſes, 12 Mahones and 9 Ships, and his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral
<hi>Baſſa</hi> ſlain in the fight in the Haven of <hi>Foggia;</hi> and
this ſucceſs diſabling his command at Sea, he made no more of it then his
Noble Anceſtor <hi>Selymus</hi> the Second, who beaten at <hi>Lepanto,</hi>
after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> ſaid merrily, <hi>Lepanto is but
the ſhaving of my beard, Cyprus is the loſs of a limb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Venetians Victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Turks.</note>In
the year 1654. the <hi>Venetians</hi> obtained another Victory over the
<hi>Turks,</hi> having fought them two days together in the
<hi>Dardanelles,</hi> the ſtreight of the <hi>Helleſpontick</hi> ſea
between <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Europe,</hi> famous for the ſtory of
<hi>Leander</hi> and <hi>Hero,</hi> where now the Turks have two Caſtles
built, in lieu of <hi>Seſtos</hi> and <hi>Abydos,</hi> made more impregnable
very lately by ſome modern Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, for better ſecurity againſt
the <hi>Venetians,</hi> The Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior himſelf adviſed the method of
it, and was preſent at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98077:15"/>and finiſhing the
work, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he takes much ſatisfaction. 
<note place="margin">Turks fleet over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown.</note>At this Naval
encounter no leſs then 6000 <hi>Turks</hi> were ſlain, and <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rath
Baſſa,</hi> Captian Admiral of the Port was mortally wounded, and twenty
ſhips of War and Galleys taken, beſides as many ſunk and ſpoiled.</p>
               <p>This Defeat ſo incenſed the Grand Seignior that the Prime
Vizier (being obnoxious to his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and diſpleaſure, for other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
ſome whereof were noyſed to be of treaſonable Conſequence aganiſt his
Life) was by a private Council ordered to be ſtrangled, and he accordingly
was executed; about which time the ſparks of that Conflagration w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> at this
preſent is maſtering <hi>Hungary</hi> began to appear, for a party of Turks
attempted the ſurpriſal of <hi>Veſperin,</hi> a Garriſon of the
Emperors, which annoyed the freedom of their correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; but their
deſign being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, they were forced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98077:15"/>with the loſs of 900 men, and ſo the peace continued in a kinde of
doubtful and ſuſpicious entertainment by both parties, who made ſlight
and mutual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roads into one anothers limits, without any declaration or
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice taking of a War, which the Turkiſh Governors ſtudied to
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble.</p>
               <p>The death of the Grand Viſier begat ſeveral Factions in the
Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery and cheif Officers, whom he in his life time had tampered with,
hoping to make a party for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and transfer the Imperial Dignity from
this ancient <hi>Ottoman</hi> Family to his own houſe, an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt never
heard of before in that Government, which hath ſhewed the moſt awful
reverence to the majeſty of their Prince, beyond all others whatſoever.</p>
               <p>The ſeeds of this Treaſon broke out and appeared two years
after in 1656, in the tumults raiſed by the Janizaries, but abetted by ſome
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98077:16"/>of the Baſhaws of his Council and Intrigue at
<hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> where they maſſacred ſeveral of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van
(the Emperors Council and Court of Juſtice) ſtrangled the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier
Baſſa in revenge of his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, forced the Sultana or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs,
Mother of the Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior, who managed her Son, and the adminiſtration of
Affairs, to flye to the old <hi>Seraglio</hi> for ſafety, and made ſearch
for the Muphtee, by whoſe Conſent and Advice (which the Great Turk always
asks in matters of life and death) the aforeſaid Viſier had been put to
death, reſolving to depoſe the Grand Seignior, &amp; ſet up his
Brother</p>
               <p>To this purpoſe they laid aſide all the former Principal
Officers to ſecure themſelves from the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Rebellion,
and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced others in their room, who had encouraged and prompted them
thereunto: Theſe men miſtruſtful of their violent beginnings, and
dreading more violent ends, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98077:16"/>thoſe deſperate
actions and Councils which this Revolt at firſt threatned, intending firſt
to ſecure themſelves, and eſtabliſh their intereſt: And thus they
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied themſelves to the Sultan, with deep proteſtations of their Loyalty
and dutiful Intentions, and that the exhorbitant abuſes and oppreſſions
of his Officers had cauſed the late Troubles, which they hoped to remove, and
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore his Majeſty to the affection of the Janiſaries, which thoſe
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters had debauched from him. And to make this appear they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
vigorouſly in carrying on the War againſt the <hi>Venetians</hi> in
<hi>Dalmatia,</hi> and <hi>Candia,</hi> as the moſt acceptable, and which
made them likewiſe more grateful to the people, ſo that the
<hi>Venetians</hi> to reinforce the places they held in <hi>Candia,</hi>
diſpatcht away ſome new Regiments, Voluntiers and others, under the command
of Prince <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio Farneſe,</hi> of the Houſe of<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98077:17"/>
                  <hi>Parma,</hi> who did that Republique good ſervice, in ſeveral
enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againſt the Enemy; as did their General <hi>Zeno</hi> in
<hi>Dalmatia,</hi> where the <hi>Morlacks,</hi> who at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the
war revolted from the <hi>Turk,</hi> merited alſo very exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from the
ſaid Seignory.</p>
               <p>The grand Seignior in the mean while doubtful of theſe fair
ſhews, and their pretences to him, by ſome of his truſty Eunuchs, and at
the advice of his old freinds, had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated ſo far into ſome of the
principal of the new ſtateſmen with proffers of his greateſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours,
ſetting likewiſe before them the danger of continuing this force upon him,
for that the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Damaſcus</hi> was ſaid to be upon
his March to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> that they reſolved to ſave their
own ſtakes, and by a timely ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and diſcovery, prevent others
from doing it before them; And this was almoſt done as quick as thought, and
the news of it not<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98077:17"/>publiſhed ſooner then by his
ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn appearance in <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> who at his return from this
his joyful cavalcade, gave order for the ſtrangling of the Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders of
the late defection, ſome of whom were even thoſe who had declared their
return to their obedience, ſo unpardonable a crime is Rebellion amongſt
thoſe Barbarous Nations, who have no Scripture, Rule, and Command obliging
their Allegiance, that there is no place left for Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, in any hopes of
mercy or forgiveneſs.</p>
               <p>In this naked compoſure of the ſtate which had been
diſmembred of her chiefeſt Miniſters, it was not an Act of grace or of
choyce to prefer, but of the greateſt neceſſity and care, to find ſome
worthy and fit perſon for the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Viſier <hi>Azem,</hi> or Prime
Viſier, who ſhould be able to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake this <hi>Corruens Imperium,</hi>
and to ſuſtain, likeanother <hi>Atlas,</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98077:18"/>the
tottering ruinous Fabrick of this <hi>overpoyzed</hi> greatneſs.</p>
               <p>Much conſultation among the Grandees themſelves there was,
who ſhould be the man Nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them in this hazardous and variating
condition of the ſtate, to the Grand Signior, whoſe own conſideration of
his, and the publick ſafety, had pitcht upon the aforeſaid
<hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Damaſcus</hi> whom not long before he had
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt out of the Seraglio to that command (it being the cuſtome to
breed Chriſtian noble Children, to the number of a hundred, for the immediate
ſervice of the Emperor, who according to his favor, or their abilities and
parts diſpoſes them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to the beſt Provinces, and prefers them
to the higheſt digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and thoſe are called at their initiation,
<hi>Itchoglans,</hi> and are taught the Rules and Policys of the Government) as
having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in him ſome aptitudes to his ſervice, in the
reſemblance of<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98077:18"/>his own diſpoſition. Advantaged by the
near equality of Age.</p>
               <p>This prudent perſon beyond the expectation of his years, not
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding twenty four, couragiouſly but modeſtly accepted of the charge,
and behaved himſelf ſo diſcreetly, yet confidently there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that he
<hi>allayed and awed</hi> that diſcontented and mutinous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of the
<hi>Janizaries,</hi> partly by extraordinary munificence, and partly by juſt
ſeverity: as he gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the peoples reſpect by his free and
uncorrupted Juſtice, ſo that of all the Miniſters that the
<hi>Seraglio</hi> ever bred, or the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment produced, there hath been none
exceeded him therein, &amp; his Fortune is highly paramount to them all. And
this is he who at preſent commands and menageth the victorious Army of
theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels with that fairneſs for which he is univerſally famed.</p>
               <p>Yet had he no better luck then his Maſter at his entrance upon
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98077:19"/>the Government (in which he was inſtalled in
<hi>Conſtantinople</hi> with moſt extrordinary Pomp and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity) the
firſt care whereof, as to Foraign buſineſs was the equip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and
recruiting of the Fleet going to Sea againſt the <hi>Venetians,</hi> who
braved the Grand Seignior and the Port (as <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> is called)
at the mouth of the <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danelles,</hi> and had continued there a moneth, on
purpoſe for an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>June</hi> the 26. the Turkiſh Fleet ſet ſail,
conſiſting of 28 great ſhips, nine Galleaſſes, 60 Galleys, and 30.
Mahons, The <hi>Venetian</hi> Navy had 28. great Ships, 24. Galleys, beſides
7. of Malta, and 7. Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſes, who keeping in the Channel, the Turk could
not paſs without fighting.</p>
               <p>There were two Batteries raiſed on both ſides the
ſtreight, to facilitate the going out of the Turkiſh Fleet, by cauſing
the <hi>Venetian</hi> to deſert their ſtation,<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98077:19"/>
                  <note place="margin">A great Fight in the <hi>Darda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelles.</hi>
                  </note>which
nevertheleſs they would not abandon, but ſtood the ſhot of the Caſtles
and them, and upon the advance of the Tukiſh Fleet, part of theirs under the
command of Captain <hi>Mocceingo,</hi> making more boldly to the ſhore, got a
ſtern of the whole Navy, and ſo hemmed them in: after a ſharp and tedious
encounter this Armada, was wholly overthrown by ſword, fire, and water, 40.
Gallies were taken, with 9 Mahones, the 28. Ships butnt, the Captain Baſſa
onely ſaving himſelf with 14. Galleys. The number of Turks ſlayn, was
reputed no leſs then 5000. and 4000. taken, and as many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſlaves
ſet at liberty. The <hi>Venetians</hi> loſt their Captain Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<hi>Marcello,</hi> 500. Mariners and Souldiers, of whom the Malteſe did brave
ſervice: in room of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cello,</hi> the gallant <hi>Moccenigo</hi> was
elected General by the Senate, and a chain worth two thouſand pound,
beſtowed on him beſides.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:98077:20"/>In <hi>September,</hi> the ſame year, the
Noble General being recrui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, following his ſucceſs, landed and took the
important and ſtrong Iſland of <hi>Tendos,</hi> (the Grecian Harbour, when
they beſieged <hi>Troy</hi>) and ſoon after took the Iſland of
<hi>Lemnos,</hi> after a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult ſeige, for the Turks eſteemed it as
impregnable, and having repayred and provided the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs with all
neceſſaries for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, it lying within view of the Enemy, and a great
annoiance to their trade and proviſion by Sea, departed towards
<hi>Scio,</hi> and now the hopes of an accomodation by a Treaty, which was
main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at this time by their Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary <hi>Bellarini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> were evaporated into the Turks fury, who cauſed
the ſaid Secretary to be ſecured, and the Treaty to be laid aſide. For
theſe loſſes nothing diſcouraged but rather heightned the Grand Signior
and Viſier, nor did they give over the deſign of reducing 
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98077:20"/>
                  <hi>Candia,</hi> which was onely feaſible by ſucceſs
at Sea, as being an Iſland, but <hi>Achmat</hi> breathing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but
Revenge and Honour, with fierce language, and ſtern looks upbrayded the
Baſhaws for employing ſuch baſe cowardly fellows, and then cheerfully
bade them equip another Fleet, and he would deſign and appoint the
Commanders, whom his own obſervation had recommended to his choyce.</p>
               <p>In the ſame time the Land ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in <hi>Dalmatia,</hi>
went hotly on, but ſo as it ſhewed the Turks had not totally recovered the
uſe of their Arms; and while a greater experience could be gained He thought
it not adviſeable to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard an expedition in perſon, or venture the
reputation of his Prime Viſier, in ſo minute an enterpriſe; reſerving
that deſign till he had trayned and accuſtomed his men to that ſervice,
to the ſame end keeping his Army in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98077:21"/>ſervice
in <hi>Candia,</hi> though with little effect. 
<note place="margin">The Turks ſeverity &amp; Policy.</note>For
nothing of conſequence was atcheived of either ſide, and thoſe ſmall
ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes that were, were equal and mutual, now the one, and then the
other prevailed, as if they bartered and exchanged Victory. For which lazy
progreſs, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, on purpoſe to ſhew his ſeverity againſt
ſuch remiſs and unactive Commands, though it were hardly poſſible to
effect more with the force he had, upon the Iſland, He ſometime after
cauſed the Baſſa, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thereof, to be put to death, at his return
from that Government; the like fate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fel the Baſſa of <hi>Boſnia,</hi>
for his ſlow and fruitleſs menage of the war in <hi>Dalmatia</hi>
aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Another Fleet as the grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior threatened was again
rigged, and in <hi>Auguſt</hi> the ſame year defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſame place
by the ſame General, the Emperour himſelf<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98077:21"/>coming to the
Caſtles to view the encounter, which was gallantly maintained on both
ſides, and the loſs nothing ſo conſiderable to the Turk; for that he
ſet to ſea with a potent Fleet the next moneth, the <hi>Venetians</hi>
having loſt their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral by a caſual lighting of the ſhot of a tire of
Cannon from the Iſle of <hi>Scio,</hi> into his magazine of powder, which
here blew him up, and other Nobles with him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the air.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Turks get con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</note>With this
Fleet the Turk re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gained the Iſle of <hi>Tenedos,</hi> though with a great
ruine to themſelves; for the Venetian Fleet, who had braved and affronted
them all this Summer, being gone to take in freſh water, the Turkiſh Fleet
took the opportunity, and landed there a great Body of men; who ſtorm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it,
were at firſt repulſed; but preparing for a general onſlaught, the
Venetian Garriſon working a Mine under the Fort, diſpoſed the powder
therein, with a Match fitted<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98077:22"/>to it; when quitting the place,
and getting on ſhip-board, the Turks taking poſſeſſion, were blown
with the Fort into the air. The Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Fleet returning, and percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving what
had happened, the Turks Fleet being at hand, prepared for the encounter, which
was again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely performed, the Grand Seignior being in view again, and
concerned in the regaining of the aforeſaid Iſland; but in fine the
<hi>Venetians</hi> got the Victory, ſinking twenty of the Galleys, and taking
four more: the reſt ſheltred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves within the <hi>Dardanelles.</hi>
So often was that little Republick in one year ſucceſsfull againſt this
potent Enemy. Beſides that, it hath ſuſtained their whole Naval Force
(and their ſtrongeſt efforts by land) f r twenty years together, without
any conſiderable loſs, and with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inconſiderable helps and ſupplies
from other Chriſtian neighbour Princes. But there is a great deal of
difference and odds betwixt an<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98077:22"/>united and entire State,
whoſe vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Generoſity had almoſt tired this luſtfull Leviathan; and
divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Dominions, not onely by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, Limits, Laws and Cuſtoms, but
Religion alſo, and proſtituted likewiſe to his raviſhing Arms by
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers intereſts, deſigns, and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>After his return from that ſhort Expedition, the Grand
Seignior continued at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> buſie in reforming his
Court, and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and other abuſes in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio, which by the
depravity of the times, and thoſe breaches and corruptions in the State, had
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed to cuſtome; ſloth, and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curiſm, and Pride the mother of
Faction, and the ſpecifick direct bane and ruine of this arbitrary
Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were extremely predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; and corruption by bribery, to which
the Turkiſh Miniſters of State are moſt ſtrongly inclined, was never
ſo boldly licentious; ſo that the vertues of another <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> 
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:98077:23"/>was requiſite to purge out theſe enormities: 
<note place="margin">The Grand Seignior excellent in
Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>Yet ſuch was the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of this Princes judgment,
ſuch his ſevere government of himſelf and commands, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of
others, and the ſtrict ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of them, that by this he quickly reduced
things to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtate; denying himſelf the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary uſe of thoſe
pleaſures, for whoſe exceſſes his predeceſſors are ſo infamous to
Chriſtendom.</p>
               <p>This ſharp and rigid proceeding with all ſorts of perſons,
eſpecially the Souldiers of his Guard, putting the hard yoke of Diſcipline
upon their necks again; began to grate and gall, and make them to wince
againſt the Government; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Perſian war was concluded: which
Kings Ambaſſadour had his head taken off for making a denun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation thereof
at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> But a nearer European quarrel preſenting it
ſelf, a Truce and Peace was afterwards patcht up betwixt them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:98077:23"/>
                  <note place="margin">Prince <hi>Ragotzi</hi>
enters <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </note>The <hi>Swede</hi> proving very ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
in <hi>Poland</hi> in 1656 and 1657. by taking moſt of the Towns and Cities
of that Kingdome, and want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men at preſent to maintain them, fairly
invited <hi>Ragotzi</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania</hi> to come and take
ſhare of the ſpoil, promiſing him a part of tht conqueſt for his
la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour: To the ſame purpoſe <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> courted him; and many
tranſactions of that nature there paſſed between them. 
<note place="margin">Recalled by the Grand Seignior.</note>
                  <hi>Ragotzi</hi> no way diſliking the bargain, and being next neighbour, out
of covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ambition came in with a great Army, and aſſiſted
the <hi>Swede</hi> at the ſiege of <hi>Cracovia,</hi> which at laſt was
yielded, and put into his hands. The news hereof haſtily alarmed the
Turkiſh Court; who reſenting this growing greatneſs of the
<hi>Swede,</hi> and the ill neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood they were like to have from him, if
once he could fix and ſettle himſelf in <hi>Poland;</hi> the Grand
Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior commanded <hi>Ragotzi,</hi> as his <pb n="34" facs="tcp:98077:24"/>Tributary and
Vaſſal, (for, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years thoſe Princes, like the other of
<hi>Vallachia</hi> and <hi>Moldavia,</hi> have received their inveſtiture
from the Turk) to abandon his League with the <hi>Swede,</hi> and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
home, reſtoring the <hi>Polander</hi> the places he had taken.
<hi>Ragotzi</hi> not daring to refuſe, marched back again; and upon his
arrival was met with a Chiaux, commanding him to reſign his Principality to
his Couſin <hi>Radus,</hi> for that he had preſumed without the Grand
Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niors command or licence to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and make
war with a Prince in league and amity with him; and withal, to reſign his
Forts, and places of ſtrength. To the firſt he ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yielded; but
the other he would by no means hearken to: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon making uſe of his
Forces, reaſſumes his former Title, and proſecuted the Turk with open
war: And at the beginning with very good ſucceſs, though his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98077:24"/>the Prince of <hi>Vallachia</hi> was routed, and 8000 men
ſlain, as he was marching to his aſſiſtance; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feating the Turkiſh
Army and Baſſa of <hi>Buda</hi> at <hi>Lippa,</hi> 6000 men taken and
killed, and the Victory follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thirty leagues: where hearing of the advance
of the prime Viſier with 80000, he retired in haſte; and making
oppoſition about <hi>Alba Julia</hi> to the whole Force of the Turk, was
there worſted: a little before which, he had vanquiſhed his competitor
<hi>Radus</hi> (and after be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged and taken the Caſtle wherein he had
thought to have ſecured himſelf) and put him to death.</p>
               <p>Before and after this overthrow, he had importuned the Emperour
of <hi>Germany</hi> by many inſtances at <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna,</hi> to undertake the
protection of his Countrey, offering to give him caution of what Towns he
ſhould pleaſe: but the Emperour delaying a timely interpoſition (yet
giving the Turk occaſion of a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel by under-hand aſſiſting
<hi>Ragotzi</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98077:25"/>with ſome men) <hi>Ragotzi</hi> died of
his wounds (received at <hi>Alba Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi>) and with grief, at
<hi>Waradin:</hi> Which being defended for a while after by Collonel
<hi>Gaude</hi> a Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, was yielded upon terms to this prime Viſier,
being the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate earneſt of thoſe preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts in
<hi>Hungaria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvanian Troubles.</note>In the
mean while, <hi>Radus</hi> the competitor of <hi>Ragotzi</hi> being put to
death by him as aboveſaid, the prime Viſier named another to the
Principality of <hi>Tranſylvania</hi> at the end of the year 1659. a Nobleman
by deſcent allied to the former Princes, by name <hi>Michael Apaffi,</hi>
(though vulgar errour call him <hi>Abaſſi</hi>) who at the appointment of
the Grand Seignior was accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the States thereof, when they perceived it
was in vein to ſtruggle for <hi>Ragotzi</hi>'s Intereſt againſt the whole
power of the Sultan, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any aſſiſtance from the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, who in
this declenſion of that Princes fortune abandoned the<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98077:25"/>quarrel, and left them to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor would hearken to any
overtures made to him for his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, upon what ever terms of
reſignation or Dominion, and his Envoys publiquely declared to the Turk as
much, who meaſuring his deſignes by thoſe fears and jealouſies which
this punctual ſatisfaction ſignified, was the more incited to a purſuance
of thoſe reſolutions, which had been taken up ſometime before at the
Port. 
<note place="margin">The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies with the Turk.</note>
And by this means <hi>Tranſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania</hi> was quite loſt, and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely
in the power of the Turk, with ſome further advantages gained for his
intended invaſion of the adjacent provinces of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> and
<hi>Auſtria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Leave we that Kingdom for a while which is to be the Doleful and
Tragical Concluſion of this Narrative, and retroſpect to the grand
Seigniors, Home-affairs, which diverted him from an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate proſecution of
his ſucceſs<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98077:26"/>in Europe; for the Baſſa of
<hi>Aleppo</hi> (where reſides the greateſt Engliſh Factory) in 1659.
broke out into a Rebellion, and threatened a conjuncture with the
<hi>Perſian,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring for Reformation in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Religion, the
latter eſpecially, having for better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence made ſome new fangled
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of the Alchoran, more to the humour of the preciſer and and
rigid zealots of the Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan Religion.</p>
               <p>By vertue whereof, and ſome former diſcontents which were
not yet quite purged out of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery, who were diſtributed, and had
their poſſeſſions in thoſe Parts, under his command (for the Grand
Signior allows each Horſe-man ſuch a porportion of ground, for which he is
to be in a readineſs to do him ſervice) he had amaſſed a very
conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Army, ſeveral inferiour Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaws dependants, and retainers
to the former Prime Viſier, whoſe<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98077:26"/>quarrel they
eſpouſed, reſorting to him from their reſpective Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments.</p>
               <p>With this power he marched to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi>
and came on his way thither as far as <hi>Scuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> within four miles of
that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and thence ſent in his demands, which ſwelling to that daring
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, as to require a reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Imperial Title, to a
pretended Son of the late Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror <hi>Morat,</hi> an impoſtor of his own
ſetting up, ſuch another as <hi>Perkin Warbeck</hi> (to whom he gave all
honours and obſervances be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the ſtate of a Sultan;) and in his right
and Title encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and overthrew two diſtinct Armies of the Grand
Seignior, that were in haſt diſpatcht to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the increaſe of more
adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and favourers of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe.</p>
               <p>He continued in this poſture, like a cloud hovering over
<hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> big with ſome ruinous ſtorm,<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98077:27"/>till this ſucceſſeful Prime Viſier having amaſſed his
European For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, 
<note place="margin">The Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition for <hi>Aſia.</hi>
                  </note>
paſſed the <hi>Boſphorus</hi> into <hi>Aſia,</hi> with 50000. men,
(more propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to follow him) being the choice of the Turkiſh power, and
with good ſpeed advanced after the Rebel, who knowing the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage both of
the Leader, as having been his Neighbour at <hi>Damaſco,</hi> and the
Souldiers, after a long conſultation with his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of War, reſolved
immediately in all humble and frankeſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to ſubmit themſelves to
the Sultans mercy, diſmiſſing the common Souldiers to ſhift for
themſelves; which being done ſo unexpectedly, the Viſier gave notice of
it by an expreſs with as much favour to their perſons as the caſe
deſerved, to the Grand Signior, who gave them all his pardon, with ſome
extra ordinary reſpects for the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Aleppo,</hi> but
preſently after, when there was no danger of the Rebellion,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98077:27"/>and all things were quieted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, at the inſtance
of ſome Enemies of his at Court, but more truely by reaſon of State, and
the Policy of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which never pardons that Crime, 
<note place="margin">The Baſſa of <hi>Aleppo</hi>
ſtrangled.</note>he and thirty more were ſuddenly ſtrangled, their heads
chopt off and ſet upon poles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Emperors Seraglia at
<hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I his treacherous and cruel dealing after pardon given, and
ſuch a Loyal Rendition of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, when as they might have hazarded the
whole Empire, raiſed in the friends of the deceaſed, a thirſt of revenge,
having yet their Arms in their hands, and the Souldiery as prone to new
troubles as they could wiſh them, and hereupon inſtantly enſued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
defection, as great alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as the former, but the authority of Leaders was
wanting to manage it to effect. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs upon the firſt news of it, 
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98077:28"/>the Grand Seignior reſolved to march himſelf in
perſon to make a final end, and root out the ſeeds of thoſe commotions,
which were ſo apt upon every occaſion to burſt forth.</p>
               <p>Preparation was made accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly for a ſolemne expedition,
and the Rebels curſed and devoted by the Prieſts to deſtruction, the
<hi>Janizaries</hi> and <hi>Spahies</hi> muſtred, and upon their march, the
Sultana, the Mother of the Emperour ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Regent in his abſence, when
news came that all was quieted again, and the chief Authors of the late
defection were fied and eſcaped into <hi>Perſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Emperor being but juſt in his way, having effected his
buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, thought it adviſeable, while the Army was in motion into
thoſe parts, to treat with the <hi>Perſian,</hi> who doubting he might bend
his Forces upon him, was willing to come to agreement, and ſo a Peace was
confirmed between<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98077:28"/>them; At his return to
<hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> he was welcomed as if he came from a Triumph, but
that which pleaſed him more then the vain glorious pomp of his magnificent
Reception, was the news of a Victory obtained by his Forces in <hi>Candia</hi>
againſt the <hi>Venetians,</hi> who having em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed the Prince <hi>Almeric
de Eſte,</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Modena,</hi> as Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral for that
ſervice, who car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with him ſome Regiments of French, the ſaid
Regiments in an expedition into the Country, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Candea,</hi> with a
deſign thereupon, were met by the Baſſa, and after a Brave Encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
and much gallantry on both ſides, were defeated, very few eſcaping back
again to their Garriſons. This loſs, and the unagreeableneſs of the
Climate ſo affected the ſaid Prince, that he ſhortly after dyed there,
(the grave of many a gallant perſon, that have ſacrificed their lives
againſt, and<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98077:29"/>for this Infidel) and was brought by Sea back
again, to be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with his Anceſtors.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The E. of <hi>Winchel.</hi> Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do
Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rdinary to the grand
Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior.</note>At the end of winter 1660. arived at the Port, after very bad
weather, the right honourable the Earl of <hi>Winchelſea</hi> His Majeſties
Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor extraordinary, in the place of Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh,</hi>
who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded Sir <hi>Sackvile Crow</hi> in that employment in 1648. to the
Grand Seignor. He had Audience in very great State, and as uſual, the day
thereof was treated at Dinner in the <hi>Divan,</hi> by the Chief Viſier, and
He and His Retinue veſted with rich Turky Habits, out of which it is not
lawful to ſee the Emperour, and through the two outermoſt Courts of the
<hi>Seraglio,</hi> Conducted into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nermoſt, and thence to a great Hall,
leading into his Chamber, the floor whereof was covered with Velvet,
embroydered with Pearl, &amp;c. the Capitzi Baſſa and his aſſiſtants,
leading him by the Arm<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98077:29"/>to kiſs his Majeſties ſleeve,
as they did ſeveral Gentlemen beſide, that were of his Retinue, but of this
an account hath been lately given; but I may not omit that it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
reported, the Grand Signior being highly affected with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties
Reſtitution, ſhould ſay, <hi>That if he were to chuſe his God, or his
Religion, he would chuſe the King of</hi> Englands.</p>
               <p>All things now ſeemed to be in a ſerene condition, and calm
from the late troubles, which had tempeſted this Monarchy; And diſcourſes
there were that the Grand Signior would now at laſt hearken to an
accomodation, with the ſtate of <hi>Venice,</hi> and conſequently reſtore
a free Trade and commerce to his Dominions, which had been endamaged and
ſpoyled by frequent Depraedati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>But as deep waters run ſmooth and ſtiller then ſhallow
brooks, ſo was it in this ſeeming tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98077:30"/>of
affairs, not but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps there might be due to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred number of 1660. and
the particular glories of his Majeſties Reſtitution, and the fortune of
<hi>England,</hi> the ſame general peace and quiet, which once bleſt the
world in the reign of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> (with reverence to that
ſacred Miracle) for that the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Ceſſation which <hi>France</hi>
boaſts to have given Chriſtianity, by the late accord with <hi>Spain,</hi>
was clearly influenced by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Native Star, and the
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of Fate, which attended the proſperous Culmination of his
greatneſs, as could be inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and demonſtrated, were it not beyond
the purpoſe of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p>Yet ſo much concerns it, that the Grand Signior took his
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate Enterpriſe upon Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, from the very juncture of this
peace; (being as under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and converſant in the<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98077:30"/>Affairs of <hi>Europe</hi> as our ſelves) par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly his ancient
League which <hi>France,</hi> gave him opportunity of ſuch Intelligence,
which he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver maintained with the Spaniard, as his neceſſary enemy.</p>
               <p>For he knew well, that the ſtate of Chriſtendom could never
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure a vacation, nor could be free from the viciſſitudes of Intereſt,
when ſo many Monarchs at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure had opportunity to project their
ambition.</p>
               <p>Nor was he ignorant of theſe Animoſities which perplexed the
late Election of the Emperour at <hi>Frankeford,</hi> nor with what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry
the <hi>French</hi> managed their luſt after the Imperial Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>Certain it was that the Arms of that Puiſſant Nation muſt
be employed upon another Enemy, whoſe ever ill luck it ſhould be to receive
them; and that he knew would be the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> or ſome
other vicine Power, if, which<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98077:31"/>was more favourable to his
deſign, he did not amuſe all Princes, and then take his beſt
advantage.</p>
               <p>Theſe undoubtedly were the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements of this his
Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and violent irruption into <hi>Hungary,</hi> he uſing the ſame
me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Conqueſt which his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors had fortunately experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by
occaſion of the diviſions and ſecurity of their Neighbours. And therefore
unlookt for, or at leaſt wiſe not provided againſt, while the
<hi>German</hi> Emperour ſtood upon his wrong guard, and dreaded the loſs
of <hi>Alſatia</hi> (which jealouſie likewiſe armed the adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent
Princes) he like a deluge en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred <hi>Hungary,</hi> and auſpiciouſly began
the race of his Glories.</p>
               <p>Now the better to conceal his deſignes upon Europe, and to
colour his aſpect upon thoſe parts, he gave order for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of his
Court to <hi>Adrianople,</hi> pretending the ſalubrity of the place, and the
freer proſecution<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98077:31"/>of his pleaſures, and vacation from
buſineſs, and the toyl of the Government, leaving the Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tana his Mother,
and the Viſier to the care thereof, as he had done before in his expedition
into <hi>Aſia;</hi> Hither accordingly he came attended as uſually, with a
great Train or Army, but now aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented to an Hoſt, as a guard of his
Perſon; ſtill entertaining the Emperors Ambaſſador, with ſhews and
flouriſhes of Peace and good Correſpondence, till the Viſier having
amaſſed and drawn down the <hi>Aſian</hi> Forces over into
<hi>Europe,</hi> while the Europeans were embo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying about <hi>Belgrade,</hi>
it was playnly manifeſt, what this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration portended.</p>
               <p>Yet the reliques of the late <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvanian</hi>
defection, were ſtill voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to be the object of this expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to
ſettle the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of <hi>Moldavia</hi> and <hi>Valachia,</hi> in a
perfect ſubjection to the grand Seignior, they for ſome late years 
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98077:32"/>having fluctuated and wavered in their duty towards him,
and ſtill ready upon all occaſion, or change of their Princes, to break out
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to open Hoſtility and diſquiet, and diſturbe the provinces neareſt
them, and to take part with any Revolt of others, and help and aſſiſt it
to a formidable, and very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable puiſſance.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Turks policy at his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into
<hi>Hungary.</hi>
                  </note>But in the mean while they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached and entred the
<hi>Hungari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> limits without leave, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged their quarters into the
Towns and Villages belonging to the Emperor, contrary to the Tenour of the
former, and yet exiſting League, which appointed the bounds of their
Juriſdiction; nevertheleſs, complying in all things with the
<hi>Hungarians,</hi> and paying their Quarters juſtly, nor taking the leaſt
thing from them without ſatisfaction, which was made Capital by the Prime
Viſier, who careſſed the Inhabitants, and treated them very humanely and 
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:98077:32"/>civilly upon any addreſs or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint made to him.</p>
               <p>The groſs of this Army, when made up by the Auxiliary Tartars,
who are hir'd to wait upon his expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, forces marching alſo from all
parts (even out of <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> where he reſolved to ſtand onely upon
the defenſive part, againſt the attempts of the <hi>Venetians</hi>)
amounted in all to near two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty thouſand men; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of
afterwards into ſeveral parts and commands, a Reſolution being taken to
commence the War.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Hungarians</hi> in the mean while had armed themſelves
under the Commands of the two Counts, <hi>Serinus</hi> and <hi>Forgatz,</hi>
whoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors had been terrible to the Turks, and were famous for their
martial exployts and atchive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but ſubjected by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors order to
his <hi>Generalliſſimo,</hi> Count <hi>Montecuculi,</hi> which at firſt
bred a diſcontent in the <hi>Hungari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:98077:33"/>who have no
affection for the <hi>Germans,</hi> nor would ever chearfully engage with them,
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept out of envy or emulation; and this is and was one of the chief cauſes
of that little oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and inconſiderable reſiſtance, that hath
been made againſt this preſent-Invaſion.</p>
               <p>The cauſe of this miſunderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hath been very
ancient, upon the account of Religion, and much ado there hath been to keep the
<hi>Hungarians</hi> in obedience and fealty to the Emperour of
<hi>Germany,</hi> as their King and Soveraign, which from being Elective, is
now, and hath for many years been made Hereditary; that force upon their
Priviledge, Rights and Liberty, interwoven with more violent conſtraints upon
their conſcience had cauſed a very great averſeneſs to this Forrain
Government, and a general defection in 1610. and thoſe years; for fuller
ſatisfaction whereof, we muſt refer the<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98077:33"/>Reader to the
Turkiſh Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>Upon the ſame ſcore it was that <hi>Bethlehem Gabor</hi>
Prince of <hi>Tranſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania</hi> entred <hi>Hungary,</hi> ſome few years
after, &amp; poſſeſſed himſelf of the Fortreſs of <hi>Newhuſe
alias New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſel,</hi> the Governour whereof was delivered bound unto him by
the Inhabitants, with <hi>Presburg</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, and deſigned
(having the Regalia in his hands which were depoſited at <hi>Presburg</hi>)
to Crown himſelf, with the conſent likewiſe of the States and the People,
he being of the ſame Reformed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion; but the Emperors
Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes in <hi>Bohemia</hi> againſt the Prince Elector Palatine (with
whom <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lehem</hi> was in Confederacy) and the King of <hi>Denmark</hi>
alſo ſoon after, made him relinquiſh his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and ſecure
himſelf at home, by which means the <hi>Hungarians</hi> were forced to
ſubmit, but yet ſo that they have always had a han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kering and ready
proneneſs to any alteration, and a grudging at, and<pb n="54" facs="tcp:98077:34"/>indiſpoſition to the Houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> whoſe
prerogative they have in all their Aſſembles highly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted and
debated.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> cajo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</note>And as
a further incentive and reaſon to this reluctancy, may be added, the general
fair and civil uſage in point of Religion &amp; Taxes, which the Turks every
where ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves in thoſe places of the ſame Kingdom (which are far the
bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter half thereof) that are in and under his ſubjection and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; not
intently and prudently conſidering, that forbearance and lenity is meerly a
temporary bait and lure to debauch them from their duty to a Chriſtian
Prince. For he that will but reflect on the miſerable and calamitous
condition of the Greeks and other Provinces which have been long ſubdued, and
have no dependance and vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to Chriſtendom, but are ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in a
total Conqueſt; is ſufficiently warned againſt thoſe inſinuating
treacherous kindneſſes,<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98077:34"/>and popular captations, which
will certainly end in moſt unſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſlavery and bondage, even to the
ſnatching away their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and enhanſing the Tax of money to the
tribute of life, upon their Mahumetanized Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, carryed every year for
the Grand Signiors ſervice to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> and there employed
and educated in his <hi>Seraglia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Count <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatz</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement.</note>But to return, theſe miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings betwixt them,
and the rumour of the French deſign, either upon <hi>Alſatia,</hi> in
<hi>Germany,</hi> or <hi>Italy,</hi> to the amuſing all the Princes thereof,
and cauſing them to ſtand upon their own guards, which remov'd the fear of
their ſupply or ayding of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, put the Turk upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent action,
part of which Army advancing upon the Enterprize, were adventurouſly, and
inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately engaged by Count <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gats,</hi> who with a party of
ſix or ſeven thouſand <hi>Germans</hi> and<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98077:35"/>
                  <hi>Hungarians</hi> together, was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to attend their motion,
and obſerve which way they ſteered, and to be ready to put releif and
ſuccour into what places ſo ever the Infidels ſhould attaque. The Count
and his men indeed behaved themſelves very gallantly, but their number was
far inferior to the multitudes that preſſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, whereupon enſued a
to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Rout of his party, moſt of whom were cut in pieces, the reſt hardly
eſcaping to the body of the Army, and Count <hi>Forgats</hi> himſelf into
<hi>Newhauſel,</hi> being the neareſt the place of his defeat.</p>
               <p>The occaſion of his ſo ſudden Engagement, was to
diſpoſſeſs the Turk of a Bridge they had laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Danubius,</hi>
having put 3000 men over to ſecure it, but the pouring in of multitudes upon
them oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned their diſcomfeiture. <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gats</hi> was highly
queſtioned for this raſhneſs, becauſe of the ſlain there were 400.
Gentlemen, and of<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98077:35"/>the Priſoners 800. had their heads cut
of, in the preſence of the Emperors Ambaſſador, which were afterwards
ſent to <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> as an evidence of their Victory.</p>
               <p>Upon the news hereof, Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Montecuculi</hi>
ſuſpecting the ſeige of the aforeſaid <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> had clapt
in a ſupply of a thouſand <hi>Germans,</hi> with Proviſion and
Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition proportionable. This Town is of a late ſtanding, as its name
imports, being built for a Frontier, upon a convenient level in a moraſs, the
River <hi>Niutre</hi> gliding within a ſtones caſt of the wall: and within
8 miles of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Waegh;</hi> It is a modern and very regular
Fortification, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of ſix great Baſtions or Bulworks, with
Flankers; well ſtored with Cannon; the Town having but two Gates, the upper
and the lower; There is in it a very large Market place, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is a place
built at one corner<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98077:36"/>to lodge the Garriſon Souldiers and
their Arms, being moſt of them <hi>Germans,</hi> who confide not in the
<hi>Hungarians;</hi> but upon this neceſſity they were mixed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Turk beſieged
<hi>Newhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel.</hi>
                  </note>The Turk coming before the Town, paſſed his
Army over the <hi>Nitre,</hi> by a bridge layd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, a little below the
lower gate, (where the River is neareſt the Town) out of reach of the Cannon,
and entrenched upon the beginning of <hi>Auguſt</hi> this year, and begirt it
round, and made his approaches, by thundring day and night from two great
Batteries, on which were mounted a hundred Cannon, ſo that the ſhots he
made were numberleſs. By which fury he battered almoſt all the Houſes and
Churches of the Town down into Rubbiſh, but made no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Breach,
which he might attempt. Notwithſtanding, the Prime Viſier, being reſolved
to carry the Town, one way or<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98077:36"/>other, concluded on an
Aſſault, <hi>Septemb.</hi> 14. before break of day, and brought
Scaling-Ladders, Faggots, and other neceſſaries to fill up the Trenches, 
<note place="margin">The Turks beaten off again.</note>but was ſo
gallantly and ſtoutly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Defendants, that he was forced to
ſound a Retreat, having loſt 8000. men at a Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, and the Trenches
filled with Carcaſſes of the ſlain. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan their fierce onſlaught
with the chearful noyſe of <hi>Alla, Alla,</hi> but ended it very ſilently
and heavily; notwithſtanding the Viſier continued his Reſolution of
gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the place, or periſhing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it; having promiſed the Grand
Seignor to Conquer and take four principal places, on forfeiture of his Head;
but before I proceed further, it will be requiſite to give you a Copy of the
Summons, to the Governour of this Place.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:98077:37"/> 
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="summons">
                           <p>I That through the Grace of God, and through the
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of our Prophet, who is a Son of both VVorlds, and by whom there is
happineſs and glory, I that am the firſt of the Council, and General of the
moſt mighty Emperour of the <hi>Turks,</hi> That is the King of all Kings
upon Earth: To you <hi>Adam Forgats,</hi> that are the Chief among the Nobility
of <hi>Hungary,</hi> do make known, that through the Command of my Gratious
Lord, I am come with his Forces before <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſel,</hi> to reduce it to
his obedience; wherefore if you ſhall deliver up the Place to us, you ſhall
have liberty to march out with what belongs to you from the Higheſt to 
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98077:37"/>the Loweſt, and to what Place you pleaſe, and he that
will rather ſtay, ſhall keep his Goods and Eſtate; but if you will not
yield, we will take it by force, and every man of ye from the Higheſt to the
Loweſt ſhall be put to the Sword. If the <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> did but know
the good Intentions of the Mighty Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, they and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren would
bleſs God for them. <hi>Peace be to the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>In the Interim, to revenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of the affront, he
received before the Town, he divided his Army into three parts, one part
whereof was ordered to march in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Moravia</hi> and <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and
front the Emperours Forces, and the other into <hi>Sileſia,</hi> while he 
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:98077:38"/>continued the Seige, which ſaid Armies paſſing over
the River <hi>Waegh,</hi> made moſt terrible Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock, ſpoyling and burning
thirty miles together. They paſſed the ſaid River the 21. of
<hi>Auguſt,</hi> but were forced back again with loſs, 
<note place="margin">The Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars make an irrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into
<hi>Moravia.</hi>
                  </note>yet the day following they came on with 30000. and
after ſome oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition gained the paſs of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, 200. Dragoons being
ſlain in defence of the paſſage, and put the Imperial Forces to a retreat
to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Presburg.</hi> After thoſe came a body of 20000.
<hi>Tartars,</hi> who took in ſeveral walled towns, which they burnt to
aſhes, with all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent villages, poſſeſſing themſelvs of the
narrow paſſages between the Hills, and maſſacring many thouſands of
people, putting others in chains, and in fine overbearing all in his way
without reſiſtance; At the ſame time, the paſs of <hi>Jalunca</hi> was
attempted, the onely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into <hi>Sileſia,</hi> but they were forced to
retreat, <hi>re infecta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:98077:38"/>Lamentable was now the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of thoſe
poor Chriſtians, who were expoſed to thoſe outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and could not
prevent the ſuddenneſs of the danger, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Armies nor places at
hand, wherein, or to which they might have recourſe for ſafety. The
<hi>Auſtrians</hi> onely by the benefit of the Garriſons had opportunity to
ſecure, and to put themſelves into a poſture of defence by raiſing
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very fifth man to bear Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this furious and deſolating
Enemy.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Count <hi>Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi> into the Turks
Country.</note>But to requite the incurſion of theſe barbarous
<hi>Tartars,</hi> the Counts of <hi>Serini</hi> and <hi>Budiani</hi> carried
the like ravagement and ruine into the Turk ſh Provinces, where they
ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red nothing they could deſtroy, and left as little of what they could
carry away with them, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged in part, having alſo defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and
ſlain a party of 3000 Turks, and taken a convoy of 300000 Rix Dollers, and
other proviſions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98077:39"/>for the Leagure of
<hi>Newhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel,</hi> with good ſpeed returned to the German General; having
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that the other body of <hi>Tartars</hi> was advancing to joyn with the
<hi>Wallachians,</hi> and <hi>Moldavians,</hi> and that they were already come
as far as <hi>Clauſenburg,</hi> and to the gates of <hi>Zachmar,</hi> (where
the <hi>Huſſars</hi> on the 29. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> had ſallied out and
killed divers of them;) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting alſo thereby the danger of being
intercepted by forces from <hi>Newhauſel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Emperor of <hi>Germany</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, at the terror of
this inroad, left his City of <hi>Vienna</hi> (now fill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Country
people, who flockt thither for refuge, and made ſad Relations of their ruins)
to <hi>Lintz</hi> another City in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and thence by his Agents
and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes gave notice to the Princes of the Empire of the preſent
dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, defiring them to afford him ſome ſudden Supplies, as he did the
ſame to the King of <hi>Poland</hi> and<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98077:39"/>the States of
<hi>Venice</hi> (now reſpited and breathing after a tedious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of
War, which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved upon other Territories) but nothing of ſudden
reſolution was to be expected from either of theſe States, and the reſt
were too remote and at preſent uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned.</p>
               <p>It was rumoured indeed that the <hi>Muſcovite</hi> had
proffered his Aſſiſtance, in caſe of an accord to be made betwixt him
and the <hi>Polan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> but there were never any ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof, and the
like report there was that the Duke of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh</hi> would accept of
the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Command of the United Armies of the Empire, and that
<hi>France</hi> offered their aid likewiſe upon certain conditions and
Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, but none of all theſe over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures produced any ſuch thing, by
reaſon of the Jealouſies yet reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing between them; though Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom
was never in ſuch jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardy; and in the mean while<pb n="66" facs="tcp:98077:40"/>for
ſatisfaction of the <hi>Hungari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and to keep them in their fidelity,
which this ſtorm had ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, Count <hi>Serini</hi> was declared the
Emperours Generaliſſimo of them.</p>
               <p>This ruinous devaſtation can hardly be repreſented by any
pen, or pencil, but from it neareſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of Doomſday; the fire
flaming for twenty miles in view, and laying the Country in a heap of aſhes,
and the <hi>Tartars</hi> like ſo many Devils haling and dragging their
Captives, and chaining them together, with ſuch crys and ejula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as if
humanity were dammed, and Nature had expired, amidſt a numberleſs invention
of tortures.</p>
               <p>This ſame mercileſs Crew having deſtroyed all things,
returned with celerity to <hi>Weiſſemberg,</hi> there to diſpoſe of
their prey, and to be ready to aſſiſt the ſiege of
<hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſel,</hi> while in their abſence the Counts <hi>Suſa</hi> and
<hi>Sporck</hi> were throwing down trees, and cutting<pb n="67" facs="tcp:98077:40"/>up
Ditches, and making deep Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to impede their further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, for they
had not men or arms to oppoſe againſt this Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Newhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel</hi> ſiege
continued.</note>And ſo we are returned alſo to the ſiege of
<hi>Newhauſel,</hi> where the <hi>Turk</hi> having endeavoured to fill the
Trenches, and knowing that the ſeaſon would not ſuffer him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
his Leagure, attempted ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtorm, which continued off and on
<hi>Auguſt</hi> 28. and 29 with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſiderable loſs, though he now
made a Breach, but the Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches proved too wide and too deep many men
periſhing in them, with little danger to the Defendants.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Another, ſtorm.</note>On <hi>Septemb.</hi>
9. having caſt great Moles of earth, and other imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments into the Graft, he
ſtormed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, beginning in the dusk of the evening, and continuing it again
till midnight, when he made ſuch a fierce Scalado (the Baſſa's
themſelvs in perſon leading on their own men on peril of their own heads if
their<pb n="68" facs="tcp:98077:41"/>men did not valiantly) and was in hopes of carrying
the Town, for the buſineſs was come to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy-blows upon the top of the
Rampire, and ſome of the Turkiſh Enſigns were advanced thereupon, which
nevertheleſs by the ſpeedy and gallant ſuccour of the Reſerves and
redoubled courage of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants, were wreſted from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels after
their utmoſt endeavours and efforts to have maintained their atchievement,
and after the ſlaughter of 500 of the beſieged, and the unrevenged fall of
9 ſome ſay 10000 of their fellows, which they left behind them; upon which
carnage was grounded that rumour of the peſt raging in that Army by reaſon
of that noiſom ſtench the dead bodies raiſed in the Camp.</p>
               <p>This trial of one anothers reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and utmoſt Eſſay
of Force proved the Griſis of eithers For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; the Turks appay'd, and taken
off their mettal, had no mind to make another venture, nor the Baſſa 
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:98077:41"/>to command it, for fear leſt that obſtinacy of his
honour ſhould ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard that and his life together to the Grand Seignior,
nevertheleſs he thought good to continue the ſiege, and his preparations
for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſſault, and threaten it hourly, hoping he had given the
Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants the like qualm upon their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, which with a little hard
duty, and new offers and advantages up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſurrender, would work them to a
compliance; and this took its deſired effect, for the <hi>Hungarians</hi>
being no way aſſured of relief, and certain of good conditions, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
their eſtates, dwellings and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies concerned, reſolvd not to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard
another ſtorm, but to admit of a Treaty contrary to the opinion and
reſolution of the <hi>Germans;</hi> which treaty produced an accord and
ſurrender upon very honorable Articles, the Garriſon and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, if
willing, to march out with <hi>Colours flying, Drums beating, match lighted,
and Bullet in their mouth,<pb n="70" facs="tcp:98077:42"/>with Bag and Baggage, and to be
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyed to</hi> Comorra <hi>nine miles off. Thoſe that ſtaid to have
indempnity, protection, and liberty of conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Newhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel</hi> yeilded.</note>Hereupon
there marched out 3500. ſound men, &amp; 500. wounded, with four peices of
Canon, moſt of them <hi>Germans,</hi> having a Convoy of 10000. Turks, who
civilly and fairly conducted them to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Garriſon, and returned
to <hi>Newhauſel,</hi> where the Prime Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er had out of a pretended
generous ſenſe of the <hi>Hungarians</hi> valour given every man of them
thirty Duckets, as a reward thereof: in lieu and value of which ſum, he found
there a 100. braſs peices of Ordinance, and ammunition pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable, with
3000. Fats of <hi>Hungarian</hi> Wine, the uſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being prohibited the
Turks, was converted into money, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed and countervailed his liberal
magnificence.</p>
               <p>The Army thus freed from this difficult peice of ſervice, the
ſame<pb n="71" facs="tcp:98077:42"/>flying parties were commanded to make new inroads
into <hi>Auſtria, Moravia,</hi> and <hi>Sileſia,</hi> while the Prime
Viſier deſigned upon <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> the Capital and regal City of that
Kingdom, as aforeſaid, and the imperial Army not able to make any Head yet
againſt them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, paſſing and repaſſing the <hi>Danow</hi>
thereabouts, and a General Council of war being called, Count <hi>Serino</hi>
newly made <hi>Generalliſſimo,</hi> Prince <hi>Gonzaga, Montecuculi,</hi>
Counts <hi>Rothal,</hi> and <hi>Palfi</hi> being preſent, it was concluded to
retreat before the Enemy, and to put in Count <hi>Strozzi</hi> a famous
Souldier, with a ſupply, as Governour of the place, whether the Turk directed
his March, but being at liberty, and facing all the circumjacent Garriſons of
his attaque, he more imperiouſly ſummoned them all together, the dreadful
event whereof, muſt be remitted to a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:98077:43"/>The other two diviſions of the Army entred
<hi>Moravia,</hi> and <hi>Sileſia,</hi> and gained the ſtrong Paſs and
Key of <hi>Jaluncka,</hi> putting the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts to flight, with ſome
Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but made not that havock as before, having Commandment from the
Prime Viſier, to offer all friendly and fair terms, in the Grand Seigniors
name, if they would ſubmit to his protection, the cheif of thoſe Terms
were, <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>free Exerciſe of all
Religions, no Taxes or Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to be payd for ſix years, and then but five
Shillings upon every Houſe, per annum;</hi> with ſecurity of their Laws,
rights, Claym, Titles, and Propriety, by which he is in all probability like to
gain ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and obedience from, and to eſtabliſh and fix his
footing he hath got already in, thoſe Provinces, which he hath once again
invaded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And thus far of their Hiſtory, now I ſhall ſpeak of
their Cuſtoms and Manners.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:98077:43"/>
            <p> 
               <figure>
                  <head>DABIT DEUS HIS QUOQUE FINEM</head>
                  <p>ALLACH HECHBAR</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:98077:44"/>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:98077:44"/>
            <p>The Copy of this Letter or Summons comming newly to Hand by a
perſon of quality, and having ſeen the like inſolence, and blaſphemous
arrogance formerly Printed in the Turkiſh Hiſtory, I thought it would be
ſomething ſatisfactory to publiſh this which expreſſeth ſome
extraordinary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and reſolution of this Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and ſucceſsful
Infidel.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>VVE by the Grace of God, Lord of many Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, Victor and
Triumpher over our Enemies, Potent Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror of the Turks, Co-adjutor of the God
Mahomet, and the Moon, Protector of the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre of the Crucified Chriſt,
Implacable enemy to all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Chriſtianity:</signed>
                     <salute>To thee <hi>Roman
Caeſar,</hi> King of few<pb n="74" facs="tcp:98077:45"/>Regions, give to know;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>That we
come to thee with a people of thirty three Kingdomes, ſo great a multitude as
thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaweſt or heardſt of before, to bereave thee by force of
Arms, of thy Crown and Tribute of thy Subjects. The City by thy ſelf
Inhabited we will beſiege, we will overcome thy ſtrong men, thy women with
child we will give to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal ſlaughter, Their Embrios as Toads we will
thruſt through with Spears and ſharpened Stakes, Thy moſt valiant young
men we will rend in peices, and caſt forth for meat for the Dogs. Thee, thy
Popes, Cardinals, Arch biſhops, Monks and Nuns, together with all their own
dependings, we will ſend as Slaves into perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual bondage, and finally, we 
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:98077:45"/>will ruine and deſtroy you all, and then ſhall you
ſee, whether your Crucified Chriſt will ſave you from us, who could not
ſave himſelf; as if we or ours could give credit, or yeild any belief to
ſuch incredible things. The very City where he was born, wherein he lies
dead, We even enjoy, detain under our Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and aſſuredly you may
beleive that he will not help you, as being long ſince ſlayn.</p>
                  <p>This we were willing to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, that thou and thine might
know the real Event and Truth thereof, as ſoon as thou couldſt expect. This
is given forth by us at our Great Metropolis called <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi>
which the valour of our Anceſtors hath taken from yours, and that which 
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:98077:46"/>we keep, and will always keep from yours; and that which we
keep and will always keep, to the Ignominy and diſgrace of you all.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated at <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> 
                        <date>in the 15. year of our Reign, and the 23. of our
Age.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98077:46"/>
            <head>A Nevv Survey Of the Turkiſh EMPIRE.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of their Oratories.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Fabricks of
their Churches are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently large and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous, and called by the
name of <hi>Meſchites:</hi> in which I never could perceive any ſort of
fancies or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries,<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98077:47"/>(for Idolatry is held by them the
worſt of abominations) but onely theſe, or one of theſe inſcriptions
following, in the Arabick Language, <hi>There is no God but one, and</hi>
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet <hi>his Prophet;</hi> or, <hi>One Creator and Prophets equal:</hi> or,
<hi>None is ſtrong as God.</hi> Then there is ſeen a great abundance of
burning Lamps, the whole Church whited, the Pavement covered with
Mattreſſes, and on them the Ornaments of Tapeſtries. Neer the Church, is
erected a Tower of great height, to the top whereof the Prieſt aſcends
before the time of Prayers, and with a loud voice, his ears ſtopped with his
fingers, he thrice proclaims theſe words; <hi>God, True, One:</hi> which
Clamour or Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry (for they have no Bells) being heard, the Nobility, and all
unbuſied perſons, repair to Church, as bound to that devotion. Afterwards
the ſaid Prieſt deſcending, prays with them; (and then they turn their
faces towards <hi>Mecha:</hi>) And this he is tyed to do by his Office, five
times day and night. But whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98077:47"/>cometh to theſe
Prayers, muſt waſh his hands, his feet and privities, and his head thrice
ſprinkled with water: and theſe words pronounced, <hi>Glory to my God;</hi>
Then, their ſhooes put off, and left at the Church-door, they enter in,
ſome bare-footed, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers having new ſhooes or ſocks, and ſo tenderly
touch the ground. Women come not into Churches, as being not excis'd, and for
fear of diſturbing mens devotions, but meet apart in ſevered places,
altogether ſhut off from eyes and ears of men; and more ſeldome frequent
their Churches, except in time of Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, or Eaſter, and on Fridays;
which days from <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, for diſtinction and
imitation, they almoſt reſpect as much as Jews their Sabbaths, or
Chriſtians the Lords day. They pray from nine a clock at night till twelve;
and in their praying, their bodies are ever in great motion and agitation;
wherewith they marvelouſly afflict themſelves with loud cryings and fierce
ejaculations; ſo as oftentimes,<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98077:48"/>their ſtrengths and
ſpirits failing, they ſink unto the ground; and if it happen, any of them
conceive her ſelf with child, ſhe then aſſures her ſelf that
pregnancy proceeds from favour of the Holy Spirit; and when delivered, the
Infants born are called, <hi>Sons, or Souls of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> This hath
been related to me from their Hand-maids; for I, nor ever any man elſe were
preſent at that ſpectacle. At mens devotions I have been often preſent
with my Maſter; whoſe cuſtoms are in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner following: in their prayers
they ne'er take off (their Turbants) cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of their heads, but with the
tops of their fingers gently touch them, in token of taking them off; they fall
upon their knees and often kiſs the ground: they hold it for great
wickedneſs, to have a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an preſent at their myſteries; for they
believe their Churches (as they ſay) to be polluted by men unwaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and
that Chriſtians uſe not ſuch Lavatories. Every Church in <hi>Turky</hi>
hath a peculiar place for Baths and<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98077:48"/>waſhings, with lodgings
for a Prieſt. Now here the Prieſt aſcends his Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit (reads a piece of
the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> and ſometimes expounds it) and there preaches about two
hours; his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ended, two boys come up to him, who pronounce their prayers
ſinging with reſponſals; which Songs being ended, the Prieſt with the
whole People in a low voice, beating upon their ſides, repeat theſe words,
<hi>There is but one God;</hi> which for the ſpace of half an hour they do,
and ſo depart. But this manner of prayers and ceremonies of preaching and
ſinging, are not done every day, unleſs in time of Lent, Feſtivals,
ſome Sundays; and moſt obſerve the Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days for religious worſhip.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of their Lent.</note>They keep their Lent by
faſting one Month and one Week every Year; but not always the ſame: for if
this Year they faſt out <hi>January,</hi> the next they faſt out
<hi>February,</hi> and keep on that courſe; ſo as in twelve Years ſpace,
they dedicate to God (in lieu of tenths) one Year and twelve Weeks. Travellers
and ſick<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98077:49"/>Perſons are excuſed from preſent faſtings;
but are injoyned to ſupply it, by faſting ſo many days at other times.
When they faſt, all that Day they taſte nothing, not ſo much as Bread or
Water; then the Stars ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, it is lawful for them to eat of all things
which are not ſtrangled, or Hoggs-fleſh, which they eſteem as Carrion,
moſt unclean. Their Lent being paſt, they obſerve <hi>Eaſter</hi> for
three days, with great ſolemnity, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynting the Nails of their Feet and
Fingers with an Oyl which they call <hi>Chna,</hi> which makes thoſe Nails to
ſhine like Gold; and with the ſame, they ſometimes ſtain or colour the
Hoofs and Tails of Horſes. This Tincture holds very long, and can hardly be
wip'd away; ſo as until new Nails thruſt out the old, they ſtill retain
that dye; but Nails of the Hand, by frequent waſhing, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate in time. Women
do not onely anoynt the Nails, but their whole Hands and Feet alſo with that
Oyl.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98077:49"/>
                  <note place="margin">Of their
Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>They Circumciſe not on the eighth day as the
<hi>Jews</hi> do, but when the new-born arrive at the age of ſeven or eight
years, and be of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſpeech: the myſtery whereof, is from the words of
confeſſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired before Circumciſion, which are ſome of thoſe
ſentences afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned in their Churches, which they repeat, and give
aſſent thereto, by holding up the Thumb of the Right-hand. The Youth is not
for this myſtery brought unto their Church, but is Circumciſed in his
Parent Houſe. I have been often preſent at this ſolemnity, which is
performed in manner following: firſt, the friends are all invited to a
feaſt, ſufficiently furniſhed with all ſorts of delicate fleſh,
lawful for them to eat; and almoſt every where, eſpecially amongſt the
weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier ſort, an Ox is killed, bowelled and flayed; in the body whereof,
they include a Sheep; and in that Sheep, a Hen; and in her, an Egge; all which
are entirely roaſted toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for the ſolemnity and ſplendor
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98077:50"/>of that day. Then in their Feaſt and time of Supper, the
Boy that is to be circumciſed, is brought to a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian skilful in that
Art, who fixing between a pair pinchers the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skin of his privie Member, to
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent all fear in the Boy, he telleth him that the next day he will
Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe him, and ſo departs; but preſently feigning to have omitted
ſomething appertaining to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, on a ſudden he cutteth off the
fore-skin, applying thereunto a little ſalt and bombace; and then he is
called a <hi>Muſſelman,</hi> that is, one cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed. Yet their Names
are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the day of their Nativity, not Circumciſion. After continuance of
this Feaſt for three days, the Boy with great pompe and ſolemnity is
accompanied to the Bathes; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing returned to his Houſe, he is brought
before the Gueſt, and by them preſented with gifts prepared for him; ſome
give Silver, Silken Veſtments; ſome, Silver Cups; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Money, and
ſometimes Horſe. Women preſent him likewiſe, ſome<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98077:50"/>with Shirts, Handkerchers, and ſuch like, according to the ſeveral
plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and abilities of the Gueſts. Women are not circumciſed, onely
they confeſs the aforeſaid words, and ſo made <hi>Muſſelmen.</hi> And
if any Chriſtian voluntarily confeſs a Faith in <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and
ſuffers Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (which often happens by the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy yoke and burthen
of their Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute) this Man is led through all the Streets and open places of
the City, to the great joy and honour of the people, with acclamations and
ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Bells: him alſo they preſent with gifts, and after free him
from all Tribute. For covetouſneſs of this profit, many <hi>Greeks</hi> and
<hi>Albanes</hi> become circumciſed. But if any be forced thereto, as he that
ſhall ſtrike or otherwiſe diſgrace a <hi>Muſſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> or
blaſpheme <hi>Mahomet,</hi> (as it befel a certain <hi>Grecian Biſhop</hi>
which I did ſee) that man is circumciſed, and hath nothing preſented to
him, yet ſhall be freed from Tribute, as others circumciſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98077:51"/>
                  <note place="margin">Of their
Prieſts.</note>Their great Mufty (as the Pope among Catholicks) cannot erre,
and is the higheſt Miniſter of all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Lay Perſons: an Officer
of great power and truſt: his conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and ſentences in State and
Church-affairs, are irrevocable; and his perſon held in moſt eſteem and
reverence next the Emperour: his habit moſt in green, being
<hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi>'s colour. There is ſmall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between their other
Prieſts and Lay-men, nor much from the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of Ceremonies (ſuch as
our <hi>Biſhops</hi> are) neither is much learning required from them: it is
ſufficient, if they can read the <hi>A L<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CORAN</hi> and <hi>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SSAPH;</hi>
yet they that can interpret on the Text, are eſteemed moſt learned,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Traditions of <hi>Mahomet</hi> are written in the
<hi>Arabick,</hi> not vulgar <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Character; and they hold it for
moſt deteſtable, to have them interpreted in the vulgar Language. Theſe
Prieſts and Governours are elected by the People; but their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and
ſtipends for their labours,<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98077:51"/>are paid by the King. They
have Wives, and Habits like Seculars: and if their ſtipends be not
ſufficient to maintain the number of their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, they otherwiſe
ſupply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by Handicrafts and Trades, or what elſe befits a
Free-man; as teaching Schools, tranſcribing Books, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ne'er
could ſee amongſt them any Printers; but Paper is there very well made.
Some make profit one way, ſome another, as Taylors, Shooe-makers,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of their Monks.</note>They have likewiſe
Monks of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Orders; but chiefly of theſe three: the firſt have no
propriety in any thing; they go almoſt wholly naked, ſaving their privities
covered with a Sheep's skin, and in cold wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they uſe the like to cover
their backs; their ſides, their feet and hands are never covered. They beg
alms as well of Chriſtians as Turks; and, <hi>For God</hi>'s <hi>ſake.</hi>
Theſe Monks having eaten an Herb called <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlach,</hi> are
poſſeſt with a kinde of fury and madneſs; they cut and wound their
breſts croſs and overthwart,<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98077:52"/>and ſo their arms,
diſſembling all trouble or pain; then clap on their heads, hands and
breſts, the ſpunge or muſhrooms of old Trees light burning, and not
remove them till they are reduced to aſhes. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Order I have ſeen, who
go with their privy part bor'd thorow, and a Ring included therein of the
weight of three pround; and this to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve chaſtity. The third Order is
rarely ſeen abroad; but remain both day and night in Churches, where within
ſome little Angles they have ſmall Cabins, no ſhooes, veſtments, or
coverings of the head, wearing nothing but one ſhirt; their exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe is
faſting and prayers, that God would reveal things future to them. With this
ſort of Monks, the King of Turks uſually conſults, when he intends a
motion or expedion to War.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Their reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s
Traditions.</note>They give ſo much reſpect to <hi>Mahomets</hi> Traditions
and Statutes, that, not onely they never blaſpheme GOD or his Prophet; (which
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us ſometime happens) but<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98077:52"/>if they finde the
leaſt leaf or ſcrowl thereof, lying on the ground, they take it up and
often kiſs it, and place it on ſome ſhelves or chinks of walls; affirming
it a ſin, to ſuffer that wherein the Name of God, and Laws of
<hi>Mahomet</hi> are written, to be trodden under foot. And no man dares to
ſell the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> and other writings of their Law, to any
<hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> or any other differing in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Faith with them,
leſt they ſhould be trodden on, or touched with unclean hands: and
whoſoever ſhould ſo do, is ſeverely puniſhed. And in this regard they
may be ſtiled far more reverent then <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of their Schools.</note>They have places for
Inſtruction, and Teachers both of Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: in ſeveral Towns, Men,
the Boys; and Women, the Girls: ſome teach Aſtronomy, Phyſick; and
ſome, the Art of Poetry; which when they do, they ſpeak out with loud
voyce; and moving their hands unto their ſides, they pronounce their
meanings. They underſtand<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98077:53"/>no artificial Muſick; but
frame Verſes to certain rules, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of eleven ſillables. The
horneſs of the Clymate, and often ſickneſſes, makes moſt inclined to
Phyſick, wherein they have ſome ſmall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. They learn Aſtronomy,
to be thought able to tell fortunes. Printing is ſupplied by a number of
writing Prieſts; and perhaps neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected (as all learning is) to maintain the
peoples ignorance, and keep them off from ſearch into the groſs
ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities of their conſtrained Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages.</note>They marry without Vowes
or Oathes, take Wives without porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and for the moſt part buy them;
contrary to the Roman cuſtome, where the Son-in-law was bought with Money to
take a Daughter. This married Woman carries no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with her for uſe or
ornament, which ſhe is not forced to redeem or purchaſe from her Parents.
Evil manners or ſterility, are cauſes of Divorces; for which there is a
pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Judge. They permit their<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98077:53"/>bond-men or purchaſed
ſervants to marry; but the iſſue of them are all born ſlaves. The
<hi>Alcoran</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth marriage, as pleaſing God and Man; and it
allows plurality of Wives and Concubines, as many as a Man pleaſeth. The Turk
amongſt his (whereof he hath above five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in his Seraglio's) nameth
her for his Wife or Sultana, by whom he hath his firſt-begotten Son. All
their Wives are uſed with equality of reſpect, in diet, cloaths, returns,
and what concerns them; and are moſt obedient to their Husbands. They nurſe
their own Children, and bear them on their Shoulders, not in their Arms: no men
but Eunuchs, are ſuffered to be with them, not their own Sons, if above
twelve years of age: they never go abroad, but accompanied with onely
Women.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</note>Pilgrims of ſeveral
Nations tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel to viſit holy places, which the Turk poſſeſſeth; as
<hi>Mecha</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinum,</hi> (as Chriſtians, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>)
where they ſay <hi>Mahomet</hi> was buried: but this is done as well for gain
and<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98077:54"/>profit, as for devotion or Religions ſake. And there
having ſeen a gilded Shoo hanging from the roof of the Church, and bought
ſuch fine linen and cloath as they pleaſe, they return home with great
advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; ſome carrying about the ſtreets, water, from thence, in
glaſſes, for devotions ſake, and freely give it to any that are
thirſty; others, do the like for profit. And if any one of them happen to die
in this Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, by what occaſion ſoever, although he ne'er arrive neer
<hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha,</hi> yet he hath the eſtimation, and ſhall be placed in the
rank of Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Miracles done by <hi>Mahomet</hi> at
<hi>Mecha,</hi> which, they ſay, he ſtill doth in theſe times.</note>I
know not whether I ſhould call them Miracles, or rather Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous toys,
written in their Book called <hi>Mehemidine,</hi> wherein they are perſwaded,
that when <hi>Mecha</hi> was a building, GOD, by the prayers of
<hi>Mahomet,</hi> commanded divers moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to bring their ſtone to the
Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of that Church, every Hill his tenth: and when divers Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains had
brought their portions,<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98077:54"/>and <hi>Mecha</hi> built and
perfectly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated, a certain Hill called <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat,</hi> and ſome
other more remote, coming thither with their tenths ſomewhat too late, and
finding <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha</hi> built, and no uſe of their ſtones, they begun
moſt bitterly to weep; which when <hi>Mahomet</hi> perceived Hills ſo
diſtreſſed, and underſtood the cauſe, he ſaid unto them, <hi>Be of
good cheer, weep not, but ſtore your tenths up in a place which Iſhall
ſhew you; and whoſoever ſhall not pray upon your ſtones, his pilgrimage
ſhall be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable and unaccepted.</hi> And after ſo doing,
<hi>Mahomet</hi> ſtruck the ſtones with his foot, and there iſſued out
Water, not uſeful to drink; and impoſed a name, and called it, <hi>A water
of purification,</hi> whereof every Pilgrim carrieth at his return, ſome
portions thereof in veſſels; and whenever any die, the veſtures wherewith
the body is to be cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, are ſprinkled with this water, for remiſſion
of their ſins. And they further affirm, That no man can come to
<hi>Mecha,</hi> whoſe viſit is not<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98077:55"/>known to
<hi>Mahomet,</hi> who reveals the perſons to the Keepers there (all Eunuchs:)
and if a Pilgrim come, a Raviſher, or wicked Man, a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, or any of
Religion different from theirs; theſe ſaid Keepers for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid him entrance
into <hi>Mecha.</hi> But the body of <hi>Mahomet</hi> is not there, as ſome
affirm, but onely an imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary form in the Wall of the Church, expreſſing
the lineament of a body, which is often kiſſed; and ſo they return home
again. Such lying follies, for miracles, theſe Inſidels are
poſſeſſed with, concerning <hi>Mahomet;</hi> and divers others, ſo
ridiculous, as I omit for modeſties ſake: yet muſt adviſe the Reader,
if he pleaſe, to interrogate any Turk therein, and he will finde I have
ſpoke nothing but meer Truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of their Alms.</note>The <hi>Alcoran</hi>
obligeth men to Alms, as meritorious, and much pleaſing God; and ſaith,
<hi>The contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry comes from the Devil.</hi> They have Hoſpitals for poor
travellers, built by the Wills and Legacies of their<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98077:55"/>Kings;
where they have meat in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent manners: ſome allow Rice with fleſh,
others prepare Wheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread, and water to drink; but for reſt or Lodgings,
there is no place allowed: yet there are ſome few pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick receptacles, where
they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived without charge, or other bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding then Straw or Hay; but
they repoſe under a good Roof.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of their Sacrifice.</note>Their Offerings or
Oblations are for the moſt part upon promiſe or vows, in ſickneſſes
or other dangers; and then they kill an Ox or a Sheep, according to their
abilities, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to ſacrifice it in ſome certain place. This
Offering is not burnt, or placed on an Altar, after the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the
<hi>Jews;</hi> but the beaſt being killed, the skin, head and feet, and a
fourth part of the fleſh, is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Prieſt; another part, to the
poor; a third, to neighbours; and the remainder they keep for themſelves and
friends to rejoyce withal. Neither are they tied to perform theſe vows,
unleſs they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the diſeaſe or danger for which<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98077:56"/>they intended them: all things with them being conditional; <hi>I give
you, if you give me.</hi> And the like is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the <hi>Greeks,
Armenians,</hi> and other Aſiatick people, even of the Chriſtian Faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of their Wills and Legacies.</note>If any of
their Muſſelmen make a Will, their Legacies are given before Friends or
Neighbours; and they are commonly for cutting Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, for conveying
Springs from ſome remote places, to Hoſpitals, Churches, or dry
habitations; and that for Piety ſake, and their ſouls benefit. Others give
money to free bond-men out of thraldom. But Women for the moſt (as moſt
ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious) bequeath their gifts to Souldiers, for a certain
ſlaughter of Chriſtians, which they conceive to be greatly beneficial for
their Souls. The Legacies of their Kings are for the building of Hoſpitals,
Churches; and ſo likewiſe are thoſe of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent and great
perſonages.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ceremonies of the Dead.</note>When any of
their Muſſelmen die, men take the Funeral-care of men, and women of women.
They waſh<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98077:56"/>the departed body very clean, and wrap it in
fine linen; then they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it out of Town, into ſome remote place, (for
they hold it ſinful to bury in their Churches.) Firſt, Friends of the
deceaſed and Prieſts meet and go in progreſs, certain Monks bearing wax
Candles; then follow ſome of their Prieſts ſinging till they come to the
Grave, ſhaking their heads, and often turning round, fall down with
giddineſs, as in a trance. The bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort have their Graves lined with
Boards at bottom and at ſides, and covered with Boards, on which they throw
the Earth, and ſtrow ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the ſeeds of Flowers thereon. Great men
and Baſſa's have peculiar Chappels for themſelves and Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. The poor
are buried by high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, or in open fields. If the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed be of poor
ability, there is then money gathered for ſatisfaction of labour for thoſe
religious Men, which is offered in the Streets.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, called
<hi>Tulbe.</hi>
                  </note>Over this ſtately Tomb, (being Prince-like) there is
erected a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Temple, wherein their Kings are<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98077:57"/>buried in
the City with great magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence. Both rich and meaner have an Altar built of
ſuch an heighth, as Beaſts cannot annoy or pollute it with any foulneſs:
thither with la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations and weepings they often return; and ſpread upon
the monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſacrifices of meats, bread, fleſh, cheeſe, egges, milk.
This Solemnity or Funeral-ſupper continues for nine days after the parties
burial, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Heathen manner) for the ſoul of the departed: and
it is left to be eaten by the Poor, by Ants, or Fowls of the Air. They ſay,
<hi>It e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually pleaſeth God, to give Alms to Beaſts that want, as men,
when they are given for God's ſake.</hi> I have ſeen many buy Birds in
cages at good va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues, onely to ſet them at liberty, and ſee them flye
away; others, throw Bread into Rivers for Fiſhes, and that for the love of
God, ſaying, That <hi>ſuch charity towards the needy, doth obtain a great
reward from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Concerning War.</note>The Turks have all one
Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour or King, of the Race of <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> 
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98077:57"/>who
hath next to himſelf in Authority two Sangiachs or Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roys, chief
Governours, th' one of <hi>Europe,</hi> th' other of <hi>Aſia;</hi> and
theſe have under them Lieutenants of leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer quality, who command the
or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Souldiery; and if they fail, being call'd to any expedition, are
preſently puniſhed with death. He hath others always following him; as
Councellors, Guardians of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ever neer him; Chamberlains, Chancellors,
and Exactors of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, for monies and young people; with certain numbers of
light-horſe, Meſſengers, and divers others that continually follow the
Court. His greateſt ſtrength is in his Slaves; Children (for the moſt
part) torn from Chriſtian Parents, with Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute-Children bred and educated
in ſeveral Seraglio's, Captives taken in War, and Renegado's. Of theſe,
ſome are trained up, and ſerve on horſe; who have a double ſtipend to
the Foot, and alwayes ready at command, in ſtables keeping four hundred
horſe together. The great<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98077:58"/>body of Foot-Souldiery are the
Janizaries, all commanded by a Chief, called their <hi>Aga,</hi> a perſon of
mighty truſt, and like importance; who hath under him divers inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
Commanders, and have Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glio's apart. Of theſe, and Auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liary Forces, the
Turk can draw three hundred thouſand to the Field. A great part of theſe
Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries attend the Court, Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors houſes, and protect all
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Inhabitants and Travellers, for rewards; and are faithful in
thoſe imployments. Their Standard in the Field, is an Horſe-taile tied upon
a pole; an Emblem of their firſt barbarity and rudeneſs. His ſtrength at
Sea is not conſiderable, conſiſting moſt in Gallies, and thoſe not
equal to ſome Italian Princes; nor hath he many, for want of Slaves, whom he
imploys more for Land-ſervices. The beſt of Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, is under the
Baſſa's of <hi>Algier</hi> and <hi>Tunis,</hi> whom he manageth with much
policy; ſometime as Rebels, and ſometime as good Subjects, to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98077:58"/>his beſt advantage againſt Chriſtians: for if they
complain of loſs, the Turk then ſays, <hi>He cannot rule them.</hi> If th'
other do the like, he'll take tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble damages.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen.</note>There is
not any of thoſe great Perſonages that poſſeſs by right of
inheritance any Province, City or real Eſtate, to derive unto his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
or Succeſſors, without conſent of the King. If any of their Dukes or
Princes deſire poſſeſſions, it muſt be with this condition; the
value of the Place or Territory is firſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and the Revenues
thereof, whereby the Turk apportioneth what number of Souldiers that can
annually maintain: then the Lord is enjoyned always to keep in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
that number, for any his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; and in default, his head is loſt: nothing
can excuſe his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in any commanded place, but known want of health
and ſickneſs. And whenſoever it pleaſe the Turk to eaſe him of this
benefit, it's at his liberty; but if not deprived, he enjoys it during life:
after death,<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98077:59"/>if his Succeſſors will obſerve the ſame
conditions, they are often ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; if not, 'tis then diſpoſed to others.
And if it happen, any one of theſe great ones have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſpeak
unto their King, with eyes fixed on the ground, they dare not look him in the
face.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of Baſſa's, who may be called
Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, Chancellors, or Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note>Theſe for the moſt part
are all Eunuchs, caſtrated when Youths, and bred in <hi>Seraglio</hi>'s, for
attendants on the Turkiſh Concubines: and of later years, ſome of them (as
I was informed, being a Slave to a great Man in <hi>Conſtantinople</hi>) are
cut ſo cloſe the body, that they often die by th' inciſion; and if live,
they ever after uſe ſmall pipes for diſcharging their water: ſuch is
their cruel jealouſie, introduced (as 'twas ſaid) by an Emperour that
perceived a Gelding leap a Mare. Theſe Baſſa's are of greateſt eſteem
with the Turk, next to the Sangiachs; and they are almoſt all that are
preferred to that dignity, Children of Chriſtian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, violently taken
from them: and none of them, although he<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98077:59"/>hath to Wife a
Daughter of a Turk, (as <hi>Hurſtan</hi> Baſſa had) can enjoy a Pariſh,
Caſtle, or Village by inheritance; but if he be promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any dignity or
poſſeſſions, he enjoys it till his death, or ſo long as the Turk
pleaſeth. Each Baſſa hath a Court of Juſtice in the Province he
commandeth, from whence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals are to the King, or great Muf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; whoſe
ſentence is concluding and immoveable.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Turks to the
King.</note>None of their Janizaries or great Captains have licenſe to wear
Swords or other Arms within the Cities, unleſs the King go forth his Palace,
for Devotion ſake or Hunting. And where there are Magiſtrates or
Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of Towns, Porters carry with them ſtaves or clubs and finding any
quarrellings or offerings at injuries, they preſently puniſh them with
thoſe inſtruments; and no man ſpeaking to them, dares look them in the
face; but falling on the earth, kiſs their feet, with eyes to the ground, and
ſpeak as to themſelves. And whenſoever they ſend forth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98077:60"/>Meſſengers with Letters to Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Cities, or
Provinces, whoſe horſe grows ſaint by journeying, this Meſſenger hath
full authority to diſ-horſe whom ere he meets; and meeting none, he turns
into the next Town or Village, and repairs to the chief Officer; and if he
preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provides him not an horſe, he's hang'd before his door: and for
this cauſe, many make uſe of Aſſes, rather then keep Horſe. And when
this Meſſenger ſhall come to whom he was ſent, he is moſt honourably
received, his Letters kiſſed with great humility, and their Contents
anſwered with incredible celerity and quick diſpatch. No Princes dare
contradict one ſillable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. None dare (as here) rebel; all men live in
ſuch awful fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling: Tortures and preſent death depending on his
will.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Turkiſh ſtrength, how
dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhod.</note>The Emperour diſtributes in ſome equality all
Provinces to his Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; but with condition, that ſuch a Souldiery
ſhould be continually maintained by him with the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98077:60"/>of that Province, both in time of Peace and War. A Souldier kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
is not loſs to him, unleſs the Province likewiſe be loſt: as for
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, The Turk hath now four hundred Souldiers, whereof one hundred is
maintained by <hi>Hungary;</hi> now if he loſe <hi>Hungary,</hi> thoſe
Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers are loſt: if he loſe no Province, he loſeth nothing; for he
can raiſe more in their rooms; as Church-Officers, or benefits, eaſily
finde in vacancies Succeſſors.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zilars.</note>Theſe
are ſtout Souldiers, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently verſed in military affairs, who in
their firſt encounters break their Lances, without other Armour then a Sword,
Lance and Target, uſing it as we do with Coat of Fence and Helmet; the Lance
being broke, they uſe the Sword, and fight vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly, always aiming at the
head or hands, and think it ignominious to thruſt at their adverſary, or an
horſe, with point of Sword. Theſe Men ſpend all their lives and hopes
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the protection of a Goddeſs, Fortune; having a Proverb with 
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98077:61"/>them, <hi>What is written, will befal them;</hi> that is,
What that Goddeſs hath printed on the head at each Man's Nativity, cannot be
poſſibly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided; though he were preſerved in a Caſtle unexpugnable.
The actions of theſe men are writ in verſes, and ſung by all Men; that
others ſtirred up by like praiſe and honour, might with like audacity,
advance againſt an Enemy, couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onſly and valiantly: and for each victory
of theſe Men, their ſtipends are doubled; and are obliged at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance on
their King, on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, with Lances, Swords, and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron Clubs: ſome, have
Targets; ſome, none; and are paid as well in Peace as War.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The order of their Foot.</note>Their firſt
are Bow-men, with Arrows, Bows and Javelins; they are diſtinguiſhed from
Janizaries by coverings of the head. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is of Janizaries, who
inſtead of Bows, have Guns, with ſhort Hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chets: all theſe are gathered
from amongſt Chriſtians living un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Tribute, by force ſnatched from 
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98077:61"/>their Friends being young, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, and educated as
aforeſaid. Theſe fight moſt valiantly againſt Chriſtians, yet have
but ſlender ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends for their maintenance; ſome four, five, or ſix
Aſpers a day; of which, ſixty make a Crown Engliſh. And theſe are
prohibited on pain of death, to come on horſe-back, unleſs ſick. There
are ſome few likewiſe, ſons of Turks, made Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries. There is a third
order, whom they call Azaplars, whoſe ſtipends determine with the War, and
are all ſons of Turks. Theſe uſe a longer Lance, with Swords, and red
hats or bonnets, or other co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured cloath, with crooked angles like half
Moons; and ſo diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Arms and Habit from th' o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther orders.
There is a fourth of the Grecian ſect, who have no other ſtipend, then
freedom from paying Tributes and Tenths. They commonly attend the Turks horſe
of pleaſure, keeping them at their own charge, and well managing them for
war.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:98077:62"/>
                  <note place="margin">Of the Turks
Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilions.</note>When the King removes from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to any
Expedition of War, he carrieth with him double Tents, that when one is planted
this day, th' other is carried to the next ſtation, ready to receive him the
day following: the number and magnitude of theſe Pavilions is ſuch, that
afar off they ſeem no leſs then Cities: round about the King's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilion,
are the Tents of Princes and great Men, encompaſſing his in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. Then
the horſe-men of Arms, two or three together, have their Tent: the foot-men
have the like for diſcipline ſake, and to keep them from cold Air. When the
body of the Army moves, Yeomen foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men clear the ways, and here and there make
heaps of ſtone, or piles of wood, for eaſe and direction of the
paſſage; ſo as even in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the night they can hardly erre. The
Army moveth at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, and till mid-day following marcheth. The King rides
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two Baſſa's talking with him, before whom marcheth ſome of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98077:62"/>order of Janizaries on horſe-back, bearing lighted
Candles in time of night. Certain Captains follow them with iron Clubs round
poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, who keep off men from ſight of the King a good large diſtance:
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theſe, are numbers of the King's Guard; and amongſt them, a
Chariot of Women and Boys, fitted for uſe of the Turk and his Nobility.
Theſe great Men, go ſome before, ſome follow theſe Captains with great
multitudes of Souldiers, horſe and foot, and all conditions; ſome for
ſtipend, ſome for plunder; but all men.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of Beaſts.</note>Then follow a multiude of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels,
Horſe, and ſometime Elephants, laden with Victuals, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilions, and all
neceſſaries for milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uſes; and where the Turk pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Tent,
there every one, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his condition, (as in a City) ſets up his
habitation; Boothes for Taylors, Bakers, Butchers, Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and all ſorts of
Victuallers: ſome ſell dainty fleſh, and fowls; and when freſh meat
cannot be had, then<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98077:63"/>what is brought upon their Beaſts,
they expoſe to ſale; bisket, dry meats, cheeſe, curds and milk. All Turks
are generally moſt patient in ſuffering hunger, thirſt and cold. They
ſeldom lodge in Towns, but field it in their Tents, neer water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprings,
Rivers or Meadows, taking more care of their cattel then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; content
with little and courſe diet, curds mingled with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, bread with milk,
ſometimes bisket: maſter and ſervant eat toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. They keep deep
ſilence in the night; they neglect ſtirring after fugitives, for fear of
raiſing cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours; which are forbid upon great mulcts and puniſhments: but
when they go to reſt, or riſe to march, all with an unanimous noiſe, cry
out, <hi>Allah, Allah, Allchu,</hi> that is, <hi>O God,</hi> thrice
repeated.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of juſtice exerciſed in War.</note>There
is ſo much ſeverity in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary diſcipline, that no Souldier dares
unjuſtly ſeize on any thing of anothers; for if he do, he dies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
mercy. They have amongſt them certain Guardians, Defenders<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98077:63"/>of all Paſſengers from Souldiers vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, with Boys of eight or
ten years old, carrying bread, eggs, fruit, oats, and ſuch-like things to
ſell. Theſe Guardians are bound to free and preſerve all Orchards,
Gardens, Cloſes, they paſs by; ſo far, that they themſelves dare not
touch an Apple, Pear or Grape, or any ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like thing, without the owners
li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe; otherwiſe they loſe their heads. When I was preſent in the
Turkiſh Army in an Expedition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Perſian,</hi> I ſaw a
great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders head, with horſe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, all three cut off,
becauſe that horſe had been found gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing in another mans paſture
unſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Celobyations of a T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> victory.</note>When a Conqueſt is declared, the
Cities ſtraight throw themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all delights and joyings. At
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of night, for good auſpice of the ſolemnity, Torches,
Wax-can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, Lamps, Fire-brands, Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works, and all things that give light,
are every where diſpoſed of throughout the City; with Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98077:64"/>coſtly Hangings, Tapeſtry, and Silken, Silver, and Gold
Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, their houſes all are covered, but eſpecially that way, by
which the Emperour entreth. The chiefeſt triumph is made in
<hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> his conſtant reſidence, unleſs occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned
by war. into ſome other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. And he is bound by Law at every three years
end, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take ſome expedition into Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Territories, for
advancing or defending his own Kingdom. I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily believe, and do confeſs,
for thoſe dayes he celebrates for Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, no Mortal eye, (nay, not the Moon
or Sun) did ere behold a ſpectacle more glorious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplendent, for
order, number, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, richneſs, ſtate, and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in all kinds.
It is impoſſible for onely man to be exalted to a loftier degree of
ſublimation, then this Pagan when triumphful.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of their bunting and hawking.</note>No Nation
under the Sun de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights ſo much in hunting, as doth the <hi>Turkiſh;</hi>
they'll follow game through rocky, ſteepy, craggy moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98077:64"/>and that, on horſeback, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king diverſities of
Beaſts; but if any chance to be killed, or ſuffocated by dogs or chaſe,
they never eat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, nor any Chriſtian that lives in thoſe Regions: and
if they kill wilde Boars, they give them to the next inhabiting Chriſtians,
<hi>Muſſelmen</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forbidden to feed on Hogs fleſh. The Turk hath
multitudes of Faulkoners (above thouſands) in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant wages through his
Empire. Their Hawks both long and ſhort wing'd very hardy. The like charge
he's at, for all ſorts of dogs: nothing can move in th' Air, or ſtir on
Land, that ſhall not be encountred, and ſeized on. Theſe charges, with
the Souldiery, Officers, <hi>Seraglio</hi>'s, and Court-attendances, are in a
manner infinite; and yet ſupplyed more by caſualities then Revenues
conſtant: for he commands all mens fortunes at his pleaſure, and is the
general Heir of all that by nature die, or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note>The
Country-people with their Servants plow their Lands, and pay<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98077:65"/>the Tenths of all encreaſe unto the King. Artificers maintain
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by Trades: who live in idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, conſume in hunger. They
eagerly purſue all ſorts of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizings; travelling the leſſer
<hi>Aſia, Arabia, Egypt,</hi> and States of the <hi>Venetians.</hi> They have
their baths in every City, where in ſolemn manner they waſh themſelves.
When they make water, they waſh that part; and the like, when they eaſe
their bodies. The like is done by Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who have hand-maids following them,
with Veſſels filled with water; and when they bathe, they anoynt
themſelves with ſuch an unguent, that within the ſpace of half an hour,
rots off all hair from parts anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Men and Women do the ſame; not
ſuffering hair to increaſe: and this is done twice or trice each month,
eſpecially when they fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the Church; otherwiſe, (as violaters of
ſacred places) they are burnt with fire. They have divers ſorts of
Artificers; Taylors, Shooe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, Gold and Silver-Smiths,<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98077:65"/>and for all ſorts of Metals; Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Carpenters, Stone-cutters;
but not of ſuch wits and exquiſite inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as in our parts.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of Juſtice amoag Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens.</note>They have
one Judge as well of Chriſtians as Turks, (but alwayes choſen from
amongſt the <hi>Muſſelmen</hi>) to adminiſter equal right to all men.
If any kill another, he ſuffereth death: if ſteal, or violently taketh from
another, he is hanged; as it happened to a Janizary, who drunk milk of a poor
Woman's, brought to ſell, and paid not for it; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed before the
Judge, denied the fact; whereupon, being ſtretched up by cords at his feet,
and about his middle, he forthwith vomited the milk, and was immediatly by the
Judge commanded to be ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: this happened in my preſence at
<hi>Damaſco,</hi> when I traveled from <hi>Armenia</hi> to
<hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> If any commit adultery, the Man is caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſtrict
Priſon; yet after divers months may be redeemed: the Woman is carried about
the ſtreets riding on an Aſs, beaten naked with<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98077:66"/>whips,
ſtones thrown at her, and a Bull's pizzle tied about her Neck. He that gives
a blow, is cut croſs the face, and led about the ſtreets for terrour. All
ſuits have this good piece of juſtice, that right or wrong they laſt not
above three days. Their differences are few, becauſe they buy and ſell for
ready Mony; their chiefeſt wealth conſiſting in it: for few have Lands or
Revenues, but who command the Souldiery: but generally the Turk's Law and
Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is in his Sword, and both oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſtifled with Fear and
Bribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, two potent and prevailing A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents. To ſpoil, to rob, to kill, to
murther, upon deſign of intereſt, he ſays, <hi>'Tis Juſtice;</hi>
devaſtation and deſtruction of whole Provinces and Kingdoms, he calleth
<hi>Peace.</hi> And if in ought he adviſe with Counſel or the great Mufty,
'tis not for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but formality of juſtice, as well aſſured
from gain-ſaying an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry.</note>Both Chriſtians and
<hi>Muſſelmen</hi> manure and till their Grounds,<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98077:66"/>Vineyards and Paſtures, and have like Fruits and Corn to ours;
Wheat, Millet, Barley, Oats, win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Wheat, Peaſe, Beans, and all kindes of
Pulſe, and Rice in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance; Linen, and Cotten wools, more then theſe
Nations; Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards like ours; but uſe their Grapes in different manner:
where we make Wine, the Turk hath a kinde of Hony with them; ſo medicining
their Grapes, that both in taſte and colour they appear al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes freſh:
other Fruits they have in great plenty; Melons, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbers, Pumpions:
repleniſh well their Fields and Gardens in their ſeaſons: Nuts, Pears,
Apples, Peaches of all ſorts, Apricocks, Cheſnuts, Figs, Lemons, Oringes,
Cherries; and ſuch-like, at ſmall rates; but not in equal plenty in all
Kingdoms: and there are ſome within the Turks Dominion, as
<hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padocia,</hi> and leſs <hi>Armenia,</hi> where, in regard of cold,
they have no ſuch-like Frutages.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:98077:67"/>
                  <note place="margin">Of diverſity of
Cattle.</note>They have Shepherds, (whom they call <hi>Sobanlars</hi>) always
living in ſolitary places, and every Month remove their ſtations: they
nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have poſſeſſions or houſes, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then their Tents, and
Cattle; as Camels, Mules, Horſe, Cows, Oxen, Sheep, and Goates; whom they
feed, make Cheeſe and Butter; ſhear the Wool, and ſo make Cloaks,
Mantles, and Tapeſtry, which they ſell, and ſupply thereby their Families
with Corn and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries. All theſe Shepherds pay the King tenths of
all annual en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe; and all Chriſtians further pay Tribute, that live
under the Turkiſh Government, for every Male, one Crown yearly; and that
which is moſt cruel, their ſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married, are taken forcibly from them
every fifth year, when their Tents are viſited.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of Houſes.</note>They have no great
magnificence of buildings; moſt of them are of bricks, but differing; ſome
are burn'd in Furnances, ſome dryed by Sun. Their houſes are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98077:67"/>like ours in <hi>Europe;</hi> but in <hi>Natolia,</hi> they
are flat tabled without elevation; from whence by Gut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Pipes, and Chanels,
Rain-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter flowes down to them. The houſes lowe; none above two ſtories,
and meanly furniſhed, if not poorly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of their Garments.</note>Their Veſtments
are made of Wool, Flax, and ſpun Silk, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently magnificent. The uſe
a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (which is called <hi>Chaucan</hi>) ſtraight, full of plates, and
of length even to their ankles; abhorring breeches, as too much directing to,
and expreſſing privities. Their ſhirts or ſmocks are dyed in colour
Violet. Their heads are covered with great rolls of Callico or ſuch-like
ſtuff, wound about in faſhion of Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mids; which they call
<hi>Turbants.</hi> Women of quality go alwayes with their faces veiled; which
are never ſeen of ſtrangers, or in publick places. Their ſhooes are high,
with ſtrong ſoles, for longer ſervice both of men and women. Some ſay
that <hi>Mahomet</hi> had a bald or ſcalded<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98077:68"/>head, which he
covered with white linen rolled up, as their <hi>Turbants,</hi> from thence
derived, and ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, for they never alter faſhions. They wear long
beards, as tokens of their freedom, all Slaves being ſhaved. No great
difference in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit between rich and poor; but in the ſtuffs. They are
religiouſly cleanly, and never ſeen to unburden nature, but always after
waſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of Viands.</note>They uſe, as we, bread
white and courſe, which they ſprinkle with certain ſeeds before 'tis
baked, and yieldeth a great ſweetneſs to the eater; which with us is onely
uſed in <hi>Granada,</hi> and about <hi>Sivilia</hi> in <hi>Spain.</hi> They
uſe much art and ſauces in their Cookeries: but ordinary food is pulſe or
Rice, ſo thickned, that it muſt be parted with the hands: they feed on all
fleſh but Hoggs. There are no Taverns or Innes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed; yet in the
ſtreets, divers ſorts of victuals are ſold, and all things neceſſary
for man's ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:98077:68"/>
                  <note place="margin">Of their
Beverage.</note>They have three ſorts of drinks: the firſt made with Sugar
and Honey mingled with Water: The ſecond of Raiſins, the ſtones taken
out, and boyled in Water, whereto they add ſome Roſe-water, and a little
perfect Hony; and this is to be ſold in moſt parts thorow <hi>Turkie;</hi>
for it is ſweet, and puffeth up the belly: The third is made of a Fruit
(called <hi>Pechmez</hi>) into Muſt, and hath a kinde of Honey-taſte and
colour with it; this, mingled with Water, is given to their Servants. The
Houſes where they ſell, are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented as Oſteries in <hi>Italy,</hi> or
Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns with us. Turks for the moſt part drink onely Water; they are not
ſuffered to buy or ſwallow Wines; and who happens to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, and
proved to have drunken thereof, his teſtimony, in all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and
actions is invalid: and yet in private Chriſtian houſes, they do not
abſtain.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of their manner of eating.</note>When they go
to Dinner, they firſt ſtrow Mattreſſes on the floor, and ſpread upon
them carpets or pillows;<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98077:69"/>ſome fit on the bare ground.
Their Tables are made of skins, and plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to be drawn open more or leſs,
like to a budget. They neither ſit, as we do, nonlie along on elbowes, as the
ancients; but like a croſs of <hi>Burgondy,</hi> with leggs infolded, they
ſit Taylor-wiſe. They always Pray before they eat, then eat greedily and
haſtily, but with deep ſilence; and in that time their Wives ſecluded
from them. Men-ſervants after twelve yeers age, are never ſuffered to
co-habitate in houſes where Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are; but under ſuch age, they go about
the houſes, ſerving their Maſter's occaſions. Captive wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have never
liberty to go abroad, unleſs their Miſtreſſes or Ladie; go to
Vineyards, Graves of Friends de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted Baths, or Gardens out of Town (which
they often do) for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation ſake; and otherwiſe are kept ſtrict at
work in houſes, not ſuffered to converſe with other cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Servants; as
ſhall be more at large declared in the following Chapter. Their diſhes are
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98077:69"/>placed at ſuch diſtance one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver another, as
'twere on Pillars, that each man may make choice of three, which pleaſeth
beſt. They eat three times a day; but quick therein, unleſs at a Feaſt,
where they ſit all day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the afflictions of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and Chriſtians un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the
Turkiſh Tribute.</head>
               <p>WHen the King of <hi>Turks</hi> makes Expeditions againſt
Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, amongſt divers ſorts of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, there alway follow him
on Camels, a mighty number of Buyers or Scorcers of Children or Men, who in
hope of getting Slaves carry with them bundles of long Ropes, wherewith they
eaſily tye together fifty or ſixty men. Theſe traders purchaſe of the
Souldiery or Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>booters, whomſoever the Sword hath not devoured; which is
gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98077:70"/>them, upon condition that the King may have the
tenth of what is traffick'd for, the reſt unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſell. Nor
is there any Merchandize ſo profitable amongſt them, nor ſo frequent; as
anciently among the <hi>Romans,</hi> who called things fairly bought, their
proper Goods and Rights, as juſt as that of Slaves.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How the Turks im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their
ſlaves.</note>The youth and aged of both Sexes, whom Chance by tenths
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriates to the <hi>Turk,</hi> he thus diſpoſeth; the elder in yeers
he ſells for Husband-men, who yet are rarely or cheap bought; for they
ſeldom eſcape the Sword, their age making them leſs vendible. Young men
and Maidens, they confine them in <hi>Seraglio</hi>'s, there to be inſtructed
in uſeful Arts for future times. But firſt, they muſt deny their Faith in
Chriſt, and then be circumciſed. And thus initiated in their Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,
they diligently examine their phyſiognomies, and the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral lineaments of
their bodies, and then the whole compoſure; and<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98077:70"/>according
to conceived ſtrength, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs of wit, and diſpoſitions, they are
deſtinated to learn Laws of the Country, or diſcipline of Wars; and in the
mean time are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed a daily ſtipend of two or three Aſpers, ſixty
whereof make five ſhillings, which they conceive a liberal ſufficiency for
diet and clothing, until they are fitted for imployments. In the elements of
War, they thus are trained, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to each ſtrength: they firſt have
given them a light bow; skill and ſtrength increaſing, they have a greater
and a heavier; ſo by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees they are fitted for expedition. They have
Inſtructors, ſevere Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actors of their daily Exerciſes; and whenſoever
they erre much from the mark, ſo often are they cruelly whip'd with
ſcourges. Theſe are inrolled in the order of Bow-men. Others are
inſtructed and made fit for Janizaries, who have appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Maſters and
Teachers every day to fight, two together with Cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. Others (an horrid
thing)<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98077:71"/>who have more lovely faces, are ſo cloſe cut,
that nothing like Man is leſt them; and this not done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great and
imminent danger to life: and if the party eſcape death, his health is for no
other uſe, but their moſt wicked luſts; and after youth's grown aged,
they are put to the offices of Eunuchs, to attend on Ladies, Concubines,
Horſes, Mules, and ſome Kitchin-imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note>Such as are of extraordinary beauty, comelineſs, or
compoſition of body, are choſen out for Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines; mean and indifferent
Faces, are appointed Matrons hand-maids; amongſt whoſe offices ſome are
ſo filthy, and ſo loathſome, as were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (though ſomewhat
uncivilly) relted. Others are ſet to womens work, as ſpinning, carding,
weaving. It is free for none of them to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Chriſtian Faith, or
hope of liberty during life. There is ſome content in hope, but theſe have
none.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:98077:71"/>
                  <note place="margin">How pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Turks uſe
Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note>Hitherto hath been ſpoken how the Kings uſe Captives;
now how private men their Priſoners newly taken: firſt, they threaten them
with all ſorts of menacing ſharp words, promiſes, and allurements, to
entice them to Circumciſion; which if yeilded to, they are treated ſomewhat
more courteouſly; but then all hope of ever returning to their Country is
clean cut off; and whoſoever endeavours it, burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is his appointed
puniſhment. Such as are thought more firm and leſs fugitive, are admitted
to their Maſters Military imployments, and can onely be made free, when age
hath made them uſeleſs; and then he is rather turned off, then remitted
orderly; or when the Maſter by hurt in War, or danger of death, bequeaths him
liberty. They are permitted marriage; but their Children are diſpoſed at
the Maſter's pleaſure; which makes the more underſtanding ſort ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
abhor marriage. They who refuſe Circumciſion, are miſerably 
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98077:72"/>and unhumanely treated; of which I have had the experience
of thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years ſufferings: nor can Lex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs in words the great
calamities of ſuch people.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick
Arts are uſed.</note>The condition of ſuch unskilful men is wretched.
Thoſe whoſe toyl brings profit, are onely in repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with them: and
therefore learned Men, Prieſts, and Noble men, who have lived in
retiredneſs and pleaſures, when they fall into the hands of <hi>Turks,</hi>
are of all moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable; the Merchant or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſer beſtows no
coſt on them, as ſcant vendible: they walk with naked head and feet, and
often their whole bodies: no new cloaths ſucceed, the old worn out: they are
hurried through Mountains, Rocks, from place to place, Winter and Summer, and
have no end thereof till death, or that they finde a fooliſh Purchaſer,
that (they think) buyes ill Merchandize; but no man is ſo happy, or
eſteem'd amongſt them, for Age, Art or Beauty, that they being ſick will
leave behind<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98077:72"/>them. Firſt, they are whipped to go on; if
they cannot do that, then they are put on horſeback; and there not able to
ſit upright, their bellies are tied on horſeback, no otherwiſe then a
ſack of Corn or Cloak-bag: if he die, he's ſtrip'd of all cloaths, and
thrown into the next ditch, to be devoured by dogs and vultures.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners newly taken are
uſed.</note>They do not onely binde them in endleſs chains, but, in their
journey, alſo manacle their hands; they march the diſtance of a large pace
one from another, that mutually they do not hurt; and tye their hands, leſt
with ſtones they miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief do their Maſters: that when ſometimes they
lead great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, as ten times five hundred chain'd together, the
ſtrength of whom, if hands at liberty to throw ſtones, might much annoy
them. At night when they reſt, their feet are likewiſe chained, and
expoſed to all injuries of weather. The condition of Women is a little more
humane; they who have<pb n="54" facs="tcp:98077:73"/>ſtrength of limbs, are driven on
foot; thoſe more tender, are ſet on horſes; ſuch as are infirm and
can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ride, are put in baskets or ripi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as we uſe geeſe. Afterwards
their condition is ſadder; either they are included in ſtrong Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets, or
forced to endure the wicked luſts of their Merchants. Where ſtill they are,
is ever heard vaſt and hideous howlings of both ſexes, ſuffering
violations from them; neither doth the age of ſeven or ſix yeers, defend
them from thoſe vitions actions: a people incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably wicked, both
againſt nature, and before libidinous.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How uſed that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to
ſale.</note>At the break of day they are brought to Market, like droves of
ſheep, or herds of goates: Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants appear, prizes are ſet; if the
priſoner be liked, his cloaths are ſtripped off, he is viewed by the buyer,
all members ſurveyed, tryed and throughly ſearched for faults in joynts or
arteries; if he pleaſe not, then returned to the owner: and this is done
until he<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98077:73"/>finde a purchaſer. When bought, he's carried to
ſome heavie ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, to plow, keep ſheep; omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting baſer Offices.
They endure there many unheard examples of calamities: I have ſeen men tyed
together with yokes, to draw the plow. Maidens are ſeverely forced to
perpetual labours; ſeparated from the ſight of men, nor are they ſuffered
ſpeech or conference with other Servants. If any man be taken Priſoner with
wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, him ſome great perſon wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly purchaſeth, to be
imployed in his Country-houſe, in Tillage, Vineyards, Meadows, Paſtures;
and Children born of them, are all his Slaves: and if they perſevere in
Chriſtian Faith, a certain time is alotted them to ſervitude, and then made
free; their Children notwithſtanding continue Slaves at the Maſter's will,
and imployed where he pleaſeth; for they have no certain nor enrolled
Eſtates in Lands, and ſo not aſſured ſeats of reſidence. If after
making free,<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98077:74"/>they deſire to return to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, they
have Letters Patents given for their Journey. But to ſuch as abjure the
Chriſtian Religion, no certain time of bondage is preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed them, nor
right of return; all hopes of their liberty, totally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>depends upon the
Maſter's pleaſure: and when they have got free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, they pay the Tenths, as
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Turks, but freed from other Taxes with which Chriſtians are
burthened.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of Captives made Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds.</note>The
Husbandman hath an hard and ſad condition, but the Shepherd far more
grievous; they always live in ſolitarineſs, night and day, cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed onely
with the roof of heaven. The Maſter and the Wife have ſome ſmall Tents;
no ſhelter for the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, unleſs at ſpare times compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to work on
Tapeſtry or Carpets. Every month they change their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, and drive
their flocks from one Mountain to another. Some Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that have more
humanity, now and then give ſmall rewards, which the Servant keeps as his
proper<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98077:74"/>Goods, and preſerves, to bear the charge of a
return to his Country, if ever he get liberty: but theſe largeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are
ſeldome done, and then, but as a miſerable enticement to ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,
thinking thereby to withdraw their hopes of ſhifting from them. To ſuch as
deny Chriſt, and are cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, knowing they dare not run away, no like
indulgence offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eſcapes of priſoners out of
<hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>European</hi> Slaves may more eaſily eſcape,
then thoſe ſold into tranſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine Regions; they paſs Rivers onely, that
may be ſwimmed over; others, with great difficulty muſt paſs the
Helleſpont. Such as intend eſcapes, uſually attempt it in Harveſt
ſeaſon, to hide themſelves in Fields of Corn, and by it live. The Nights
they tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, the Day lie cloſe in Corn, Woods or Marſhes; and rather
chuſe to be devoured by Wolves, then brought back to their
Tyger-Maſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Out of leſſer <hi>Aſia.</hi>
                  </note>Who
flee from thence, repair to the Helleſpontick Sea, between
<hi>Calli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis,</hi> and thoſe Towers of <hi>Seſtes</hi> and 
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98077:75"/>
                  <hi>Abidos,</hi> now called by the Turks <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaz
Aſer,</hi> that is, <hi>Caſtles on the mouth of the Sea,</hi> where the
Waters are ſtraight and narrow; hither they come with Saws and Ropes, cut
Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-trees, and tie them faſt together, to ſerve and ſave themſelves
for ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping; carrying nothing with them but ſalt. If Winde and Fortune
fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, in three or four hours they are waſted over; if otherwiſe, they
pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in the Sea, or reforc'd again up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Coaſt of <hi>Aſia:</hi>
if ſafely paſs, they then betake themſelves to the Mountains, and by
inſpection of the Pole and the Star <hi>Bootes,</hi> they tend their way
North-ward; and ſuſtain themſelves with Acorns and Herbs ſod in ſalt.
If many flie together in ſociety, ſometimes in Night, they ſet upon the
Shepherds, and what they finde of Victuals take from them; ſometime they
kill, and are ſometime killed, or taken and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to their old Maſters
and Drudgeries: but the ſeveral dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of travelling, conſumes more then
eſcape, by ſhipwrack, the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98077:75"/>ſword, wilde
beaſts, and ſtarving hunger.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitives.</note>Some
are hanged up by the heels, and moſt cruelly ſcourged; and if commit
murther, the ſoles of his feet are all ſlaſhed into furrows, and ſalt
ſtuffed in. Some have great iron Chains, faſtned on their necks, and forced
to wear them day and night, and as long as the Maſter pleaſeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The charity of <hi>Greeks</hi> and
<hi>Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> to Captives.</note>Death, and confiſcation of all ſorts
of Goods, is inflicted on thoſe who undertake, procure, or aſſiſt
Captives in their flight, or running a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, yet notwithſtanding both
<hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Armenians</hi> ceaſe not to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them, being
Chriſtians, to hide them, and in diſguiſes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct them unto
ſhippings of the Venetians or other Chriſtians, and freely give them good
proviſions and all things neceſſary for their journeys; nor do they
ſpare or omit any kinde of piety towards them; for they confeſs to have had
heard the like experience from Chriſtians charity, when as they
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98077:76"/>travel for conſcience ſake to <hi>Rome</hi> or
<hi>Compoſtella.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Incan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Turks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitives.</note>They have certain kind of charms, which they think can draw
them off from flying. The name of the Slave is written in a Schedule of Paper,
which is hung up in his Tent or honſe: then with vengeable and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
curſes, his head is charged and threatned, conceiving this by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils
help, the Fugitive will be affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with meeting of Lyons and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons in
his Journey, or that the Seas or Rivers will ſwallow him, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens will
grow dark, and theſe aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments will bring him back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The memory of Chriſt by degrees loſt
informer Chriſtian Provinces.</note>There is ſome memory yet left of the
expugnation of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the Kingdoms of <hi>Greece, Alania,
Vala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia,</hi> and <hi>Servia,</hi> now reduced to Provinces. Theſe, for a
long time, conſtantly retained the Chriſtian Faith, but their Children have
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got it; and there will come to paſs a full oblivion of Chriſt. And
likely it is to fall out ſo in <hi>Croatia, Hungary</hi> and
<hi>Sclavonia,</hi> which are now Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taments<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98077:76"/>and Adjuncts
to the Turkiſh Empire.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the conquered.</note>When a
Province is ſubdued and taken, all ſorts of Goods movea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and immoveable
are given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way for ſpoil. They totally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate the whole Nobility; but
eſpecially the Princely Iſſue. And when they took <hi>John</hi> the
King's Son of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and favoured him with life, it was on good
advice, that if <hi>Hungary</hi> where loſt again, they might imploy and
involve him into any new incumbrances; and when the Province ſhould be in a
quiet and calme condition, then to diſpatch him: for in ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects,
the Turk regards neither Kindred, Father, or Brother; he ſpares none. And if
they do kill and murther not all Church and Clergy-men they take; yet they
expoſe them to all ſcorn, naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and beggery, deſpoyling them of
all their Fortunes, Goods, and Dignities. Their Bells, their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, and other
Inſtruments and Ornaments of Churches, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels, <pb n="62" facs="tcp:98077:77"/>and
Devotions, they raven and tear from the Temples, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning them with
conſecration to their <hi>Mahoment;</hi> leaving onely the moſt miſerable
and wretched Chappels to the Chriſtians, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are forbid publick
Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and may pray ſeemingly in ſilence: which Chappels, when either
Earth-quake, Fire, Tempeſt, or Age deſtroy, they muſt in no ſort
re-edifie. Preaching or read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing parts of the Scripture is utterly forbidden.
It is a ſin to admit a Chriſtian to any publick Office, to wear, have Arms
or habit like a Turk: or elſe to uſe the recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of cheerfulneſs, as
Pageants, Playes, or Dancings. If they injure Chriſt or you with bitter or
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacious words, you muſt be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and endure it. If you ſpeak
ought againſt their profeſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, you are forced to
Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion; and but to whiſper againſt <hi>Mahomet,</hi> Fire and
Brimſtone fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. If a Chriſtian on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back paſs by a
<hi>Muſſelman,</hi> (that is,<pb n="63" facs="tcp:98077:77"/>one initiated in the
Turkiſh Faith) he muſt, on neceſſity, light from his horſe, and
bowing down his head worſhip him; which if omitted, he ſtraight is knocked
down with clubs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Condition of Prieſts and Fryers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
Tribute.</note>Prieſts and Fryers are held the worſt of Men, and are
eſteemed by Turks the very Sacriledge and Scandal of God and mankinde. They
have no benefit from Churches. Upon ſome feſtival dayes, a little bread is
given them by poor Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and not on other dayes. They get their livelihood by
carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wood; their cuſtome being to cut down ſticks in Woods, lade them
on Aſſes; and with this Merchandize, they cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Streets, <hi>Wood
to be ſold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of Chriſtians.</note>They pay
a part of all encreaſe, not onely of Corn and Cattle, but even Mechanicks pay
it out of all their profits. And then they pay another ſubſidie, for every
ſingle man through a Family, each head a Crown. If Parents<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98077:78"/>refuſe this Tribute, their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are taken from them, and made
Slaves. Others are bound in Chains, and beg from door to door to pay this
Crown; which if they cannot this way procure, they are caſt into perpetual
Priſon; and when all Duties are performed, it is yet lawful for the Turk to
chuſe the beſt amongſt his Children, whom he circumciſeth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves
from all approach or ſight of Parents, and breeds him for his Wars, ne'er to
return to his Friends; and ſo a childe eaſily forgets both Chriſt, his
Parents and his kindred; that after, if he chance in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with them, he
ſhall not know them. No Man can expreſs by Words, the Lamentations, Cries,
Tears and grievous ſighs, at this diſtraction of Children. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to
ſee his Son (educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the fear of Chriſt) torn from him, and made an
Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Satan, to oppoſe Chriſt; hurried from his Mother, to live
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually with ſtrangers, leaving<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98077:78"/>whatſoever is dear
in blood, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in ſociety, or loving in famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity, with an
everlaſting dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liction: after liſted in the ranks of thoſe the
<hi>Greeks</hi> call Fatherleſs and Motherleſs: yet many of theſe,
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they have denied Chriſt, carry about them the Goſpel of St.
<hi>John,</hi> (<hi>In the beginning was the word,</hi> &amp;c. in
<hi>Greek</hi> or the <hi>Arabick</hi> tongue) as an Amulet or preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative
in their Armpits; and with great deſire they expect the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Sword
(according to ſome Turkiſh prophecies) ſhould revenge and free them from
thoſe great afflictions and perſecutions; and that if Chriſtians do it
not, whatever is the cauſe, or with what minde ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever hindred; all very
ill deſerve of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A Narration of a diſpute with a <hi>Turk.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter I had travelled with much labour and many dangers the 
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:98077:79"/>better parts of the world, and ſeen many pleaſant Towns
and Countries, as <hi>Socrates, Plato,</hi> and other Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers had
diligently done; at length I arrived at the famous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Hungary,
Varadinum,</hi> where by chance I met one <hi>Dervis Gſielebi,</hi> a skilful
man in the Laws of <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met;</hi> who having diſpatched his buſineſs
with the Governour, he ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much deſired conference with ſome Chriſtian
about Religion on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide. This motion of his being publiſhed by an
Interpreter, and none for divers days appearing to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, in defence
of the Chriſtian cauſe, though many Religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were in that Town,
(ſtruck mute and ſpeechleſs at the courage of one Ethnick Infidel) who
ſeemed to me like <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that durſt not adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on one
uncircumciſed <hi>Goliah,</hi> provoking them. This I perceiving, and
grieving in my ſpirit, that in ſuch plenty of Clerks and learned men, none
was ſo well armed with Truth as durſt (though by Interpreters) reprove the
inſolence of ſuch an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then;<pb n="67" facs="tcp:98077:79"/>then; and fearing that
ſo wicked and deteſtable a ſilence, in ſo good a Cauſe, with ſo bad
a Man, would betray the Truth, and render our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt's
Opinion with him more ignominious; I my ſelf, though never called to
Eccleſiaſtical Function, undertook the charge of arguing this point of
Piety with him; and ſo a prefixed day was agreed on between us; when
multitudes of of people of each Religion, came Spectators of the event. The
place was in a Monaſtery of <hi>Franciſcans;</hi> the day,
<hi>Whitſon</hi>-Sunday, day of Pentecoſt; where he moved to me firſt
this Queſtion: <hi>Where God had his being, before the Heavens and Earth, and
therein all things elſe were created?</hi> Which Queſtion, though it
ſeemed to me not much pertinent to our purpoſe, yet leſt he ſhould
ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine us ignorant of our great God's univerſal preſence, I ſaid, He
then was in his own being. But when that ſeemed to him ſomewhat obſcure,
and that he did not ſufficiently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, I then told him, He was 
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:98077:80"/>where he now is. Which he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, denied in the
general, and ſaid, <hi>Not ſo; but that he then was in a bright cloud.</hi>
Which, when he earneſtly affirmed, I quoted <hi>Geneſis;</hi> (for they
alſo read the books of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and the Prophets) and ſaid, If
God were in a Cloud, before the Foundation of Heaven and Earth, then that Cloud
muſt be created be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them both: and upon further argument on this point,
being at laſt convicted, he would diſpute no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in it; but gave me
leave to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound ſome Queſtion to him; and for ſolemnity of that days
ſake, I thought fit to ſay ſomething thereof; and finding theſe words
<hi>(In the name of God, his mercies, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of them)</hi> in their
<hi>Alcoran,</hi> in the <hi>Arabian</hi> Tongue and Character, I deſired him
to read them: The my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the holy Trinity. Which when he had
conſidered, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at, he ſaid, <hi>Chriſtian, from whence had you
this? for in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of all our actions, we</hi> Muſſelmen <hi>uſe
theſe three words, and prefix them<pb n="69" facs="tcp:98077:80"/>to every Chapter of
our</hi> Alcoran; <hi>when we ſit down to eat, when we go to pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, when
we waſh our hands, or other parts of our bodies, theſe words we firſt
pronounce; and theſe actions finiſhed, we ſprinkle our heads with water,
and repeat theſe words,</hi> In the Name of God, his Mercies, and the Spirit
of them. When thus he had confeſſed the Truth, I deſired to underſtand
from him what he meant by the word <hi>Mercies:</hi> who replied, <hi>He
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood it literally, without other ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi> Then I applied
my ſelf to the myſtical Interpretation, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided it according to Truth
into three Perſons, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, and ſhewed
them written in the <hi>Arabick</hi> tongue. And when he ſaw I had mentioned
the Son of God, he queſtion'd, <hi>How God could have a Son? ſince
according to their Law, and Doctrine of Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, God had neither Wife nor
Childe.</hi> To whom I anſwered, according to my weak underſtanding and
capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; We Chriſtians call God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for his Creatures ſake,
being<pb n="70" facs="tcp:98077:81"/>the firſt creating Cauſe, and ſole Preſerver
of all created, who was for ever in the ſame Eſſence he now is in, and
will be for Eternity; and is the firſt Perſon in the Trinity. We believe
the Son, (who by <hi>Mahomet</hi> in the <hi>Arabick</hi> phraſe is called
<hi>Rah<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and ſignifieth <hi>Mercies,</hi> ſo chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him) to
be likewiſe God, not according to fleſh (for God is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) born of a
Woman; but of the Eſſence and ſubſtance of God Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent, begotten by
God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to put away the ſins of the World, and ſo took humane
fleſh, by the Holy Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> ſuffered for us, died, and was
buried, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſayings of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets aroſe again the
third day, and aſcended into Heaven, and ſitteth at the right hand of God
the Father, there to judge the quick and the dead, to render immortal
happineſs to thoſe that have faith in him, and to the unfaithful
everlaſting puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>I then Preſented him a Crucifix, and ſaid, Behold this now,
and ſee if<pb n="71" facs="tcp:98077:81"/>
                  <hi>Mahomet</hi> did unworthily call the Son of
the eternal God by Name of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, when with Arms thus ſtretched forth, he
calls poor ſinners to his embraces, ſaying, <hi>Come unto me all ye that
labour, and are burthened with ſins, and I will refreſh you.</hi> And to
render him more capable of the Trinity, I pointed to the Sun, ſaying, You
have a fair ſimilitude here: as there is but one Sun, that hath form, heat
and light; ſo there is but one God and Father, who hath Son, and the Holy
Spirit, which you call <hi>Rucahim,</hi> conſiſting of three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
equally of one ſubſtance, and from Eternity coexiſting.</p>
               <p>This compariſon wrought in him a belief in God the Father, his
onely begotten Son, and the Holy Ghoſt; a Trinity in Unity. And when he had
heard my weak diſcourſes of God the Father, God the Son, and God the holy
Ghoſt, he much admired, ſaying, <hi>O God, O God; I nor any of our Sect,
could ever imagine, you had ſuch good thoughts of God; for we conceive you
live in darkneſs of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding:<pb n="72" facs="tcp:98077:82"/>but by your
relation, it ſeems you have great apprehenſions of him; and believe well,
if you did not neglect our great Prophet of God,</hi> Mahomet. I ſaid, What
ſhall we do with the toyes and dreams of <hi>Mahomet?</hi> for beſides
Baptiſm and the myſtery of the Trinity, which were had from Chriſtians,
we know the <hi>Alcoran</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains nought that tends to Truth. Then I
alledged to him the fancies and filly trifles of <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s two Angels
called <hi>Arot</hi> and <hi>Marot,</hi> whom <hi>Mahomet</hi> ſays, That God
did ſend from Heaven, to miniſter juſtice unto mortal men, commanding
them to forbid drinking of wine, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful mixtures with women, and to
ſhew the way to heaven to no man: Theſe Angels tranſgreſſing Divine
Commandment, were defiled, decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and made drunk by a Woman, and ſhewed
to <hi>Mahomet</hi> the way to heaven; whom, when God ſaw there, he asked the
Angels ſtanding by, who it was that came in that ſhape thither? And the
Angels telling him it was by the error of <hi>Arot</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rot;</hi> 
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:98077:82"/>he turn'd the Woman into a Star, and ſent thoſe Angels
chained into a well, to be puniſhed everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly. Divers like ridiculous
ſtories I related; as that of the Beaſt <hi>Baraile,</hi> who could ſpeak
as man, who carryed <hi>Mahomet</hi> to heaven, where himſelf confeſſeth
to have ſeen great Angels with many heads, and thoſe ſpeaking many
Languages in divers Tongues; which is ſufficiently fooliſh, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy
the name of a Prophet; but ſaid, I know not whether oppreſſed with Wine,
in ſleep he dreamed to have ſeen ſuch miracles, or monſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities in
his imaginations. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when he inſerts ſuch follies in his
<hi>Alcoran,</hi> he deſerves not the Title of a Prophet from any
reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable man.</p>
               <p>Having heard this, ſomewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſhed, he aroſe, and would
argue no further: but led me into the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſhewed me certain Images
carved in wood; and asked me, <hi>If we did worſhip thoſe ſilmilitudes of
men or adore them?</hi> I anſwered, No; think not we worſhip the ſtone or
timber wherein theſe ſigures are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graved;<pb n="74" facs="tcp:98077:83"/>they are
uſed and reſpected onely as records and remembrances to mens mindes of the
paſſions and ſufferings of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, for the
redemption of our tranſgreſſions: and we worſhip our true God in minde
and Spirit, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred by that Crueifix; neither are you denied the like
remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances of your great Princes, and famous men, nor we of holy Saints; but
'tis to give God thanks for their examples of holineſs, and our prayers to
imitate their charity and pieties.</p>
               <p>In theſe diſcourſings, he ſpies ſome dogs walking in
the Church, and doing ſomething againſt an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, (an evil cuſtom, and
to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by all) and asked whether it was lawful for Beaſts to enter
our Churches? and bluſhing with ſhame, not knowing how to defend this
neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of Chriſtian Paſtors, I told him, It was neither lawful nor
ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and deſired him to conceive it a meer negligence of Officers.</p>
               <p>When he heard this, he commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it very much, and deſired me
to inſtruct him in our Saviour's Prayer,<pb n="75" facs="tcp:98077:83"/>which I gave him
after, in the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian</hi> Dialect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A Lamentation for loſs of Chriſtians deſtroyed.</head>
               <p>AFflicted with an infinite and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible ſorrow (moſt high
and mighty Monarchs and Governors of Chriſtian Commonwealths) to ſee the
ſad condition, and moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble being of our Brethren under the
Turkiſh ſlavery; whereof ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from the boſome of our Church
to heretical unhappineſs; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with civil and hoſtile ſword, ſlain,
murthered, and caſt to devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Beaſts; others made captive to perpetual
ſervitude, and moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly afflicted: They all by me in lamentable ſobs
and groanings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, O monſtrous, miſchievous am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of ill men, and
wicked cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs of ruling! How many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual ſouls conſecrated to
Gods Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, have you betrayed to Death and to the Devil? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Principalities and Kingdoms of<pb n="76" facs="tcp:98077:84"/>great Kings, and all ſorts
of Nobility, have you deſtroyed? How many walls of ſtately Towns have you
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed? How many ſumptuous Palaces and ſtrong ſtately Caſtles
have you levelled with the ground? How many lawful Owners have you dejected
from eminent Eſtates and quiet Conditions, and baniſhed to perpetual
diſconſolations?</p>
               <p>And although I intend not to write the Acts of Princes, but to
delineate the calamities and tragedies of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, I cannot forbear
remembrance of that abominable diſcord of the Earl of <hi>Servia,</hi> a
potent and proud Prince, who agreeing (a ſhameful foul example of a vitious
ambition) with the Baſſa of <hi>Boſnia,</hi> (his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Enemy) and
having many Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and ſtrong holds upon the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Confines, even to
the River <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus,</hi> (which divides <hi>Illyria</hi> from
<hi>Croa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi>) and defended all thoſe Provinces which lye between that
River and the River <hi>Dravus,</hi> from Turkiſh vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences and
incurſions: This Earl or Lord of <hi>Servia,</hi> falling into variance and
ſome petty controverſies with<pb n="77" facs="tcp:98077:84"/>the Nobility of
<hi>Sclavonia,</hi> made friendſhip with the ſaid Baſſa, and joyning
their Armies both together, invaded the <hi>Sclavonians,</hi> partly at
difference between themſelves, and partly impotent; wholly deſtroys them
and their Province with fire and ſword, ruining their Towns and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
ſome by violence and force, ſome by craft and treachery, (cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary with
wicked men and Turks) and ſo totally vanquiſhed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered them. And
after a few Months had paſſed, this Baſſa behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Earls rich
Provinces, and neighbouring with his, he took or made occaſions to invade
him, whom at length he kill'd; and ſo reduced all his Territories under the
Turkiſh Government. Thus this ſeditious Atheiſt, Traytor to his Country
and his Brethren, moſt ignominiouſly loſt his life: for ſuch are the
Turks re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to whomſoever by craft, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, or villanous fraud, he can
lay hold on or enſnare. The like was done with ſome Noble-men of
<hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> whom they reduced to miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble captivity.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:98077:85"/>Wherefore (moſt Chriſtian Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs) the
cruelties of this Tyrant ought with all induſtry and vigilance be both feared
and prevented; leſt conſidering your fair Provinces, and viewing them with
a faſcinating eye, he find you diſagreeing, and thereby infeebled, he
aſſault you on all fides, not only <hi>Candia, Calabria, Malta,</hi> and
<hi>Sicily,</hi> but even <hi>Italy, France, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Germany;</hi>
and prove an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal ſcourge and terrour to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome. They
are wiſe, who by others harms prevent their own: you are concerned when your
neighbors houſe is fired. But not to trouble you in this kinde, I recommend
to you, moſt prudent Governours, the correction and amendment of this great
errour, and return to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable calamities and afflictions our Brethren
ſuffer under the yoke of Tribute in the Turks Dominions, where ſome with
chains about their necks are dragged through ſharp and ſpiny parts of
<hi>Thracia</hi> and leſſer <hi>Aſia,</hi> with naked feet, in thirſt
and hunger: and if by labour of long journeys, diſeaſes, or other griefs
they die, (as<pb n="79" facs="tcp:98077:85"/>often happens to men of Quality and bred in
eaſe) are hurled ſtript in the next ditch, (though not half dead) to the
care of ravenous fowls; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that is, young people of either ſex, endure
perforce the filthy luſts of their buyers and their defencers, with hideous
cryes and howlings of viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and vitiated people; the age of ſix years not
defending them: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ignorant in husbandry or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick Arts, and literated
men (who are leaſt ſaleable) are for long time driven from Town to Town,
from Street to Street; and being once ſold, compell'd with clubs and
ſcourges to learn Trades and daily employments in baſe buſineſſes and
grievous pains: others of more ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtious ſtrength, are made ſlaves to
Gallies, tied by the legs with chains, and moſt miſerably tortured; whoſe
ſad calamities the power of humane wit cannot expreſs in words. And if
theſe poor unfortunate ſouls could have foreknown that miſerable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
they'd rather have choſen a thouſand deaths. If pains of life and death
were e'er commix'd together;<pb n="80" facs="tcp:98077:86"/>yea, if to live long and many
days, and die every hour, were ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, it is in <hi>Turkie: Egyptian</hi>
ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, <hi>Babylonian</hi> baniſhment, <hi>Aſſyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack</hi>
captivity, <hi>Roman</hi> deſtruction, are toyes and trifles to theſe
calamities. People, who live as it were in the firy Furnace of the <hi>Chaldean
Hut,</hi> and crying up to heaven, with ſighs and groans, <hi>O Lord, how
long! ariſe, and forſake us not in the end:</hi> and when oppreſſed and
grieved beyond all hope, they turn their eyes again on their own Countries,
likewiſe in captivity; yet wiſh themſelves ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſlaves there, then
where they are: their prayers are not for liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but change of place; and
for that cauſe, indifferent for death or or life, they turn Fugitives; and
ſome leaving their flocks in deſerts, their Oxen at plow, expoſe
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to devouration; ſome mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering their Maſters and their
Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; ſome burning their houſes in revenge; ſome run away, hiding
themſelves in Caves and hollow Trees, with fearful wants and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; which
I here forbear, having<pb n="81" facs="tcp:98077:86"/>given the Reader ſome taſte
thereof before. And now they turn their cries to you, all Chriſtian Monarchs
and Governours of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths.</p>
               <p>Imploring and beſeeching the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> who
ſhould be Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Country, and all ſorts of men belonging to
Chriſt his holy Church, That they uniting all ſects of men in peace and
concord, would labour to ſuppreſs this common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and reſtore their
Brethren unto liberty.</p>
               <p>Imploring and beſeeching the Emperor and all Imperial Princes,
Dukes, Cities, and Nobility, to cool their hot Calentures of ambition, and
avarice of neighbours rights, and ſet apart domeſtick quarrels, and call
together and unite their ſtrengths againſt ſo cruel an Uſurper, and
hoſtile Enemy, and labour to defend their preſent, or elſe recover their
loſt Territories; and then be aſſured, the circumſpection of the
Spaniſh Souldiery, the warlike fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Belgick Provinces, the
quick prudence of the Italian w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, 
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:98077:87"/>the robuſtiouſneſs and ſtoutneſs of the Germans,
will be eaſily perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the King of Romans, againſt this univerſal
Enemy; remembring you withal, No Crown ſits ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly on an Emperor
or Princes head, as that which beareth a true Title of the Peoples ſafety and
law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Liberties.</p>
               <p>Imploring and beſeeching the moſt Chriſtian King of
<hi>France,</hi> to employ his helping and heroick Arms, in ſafeguard
(according to his Title) of his Chriſtian Brethrens liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and his own
from Turkiſh Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny.</p>
               <p>Imploring and beſeeching the moſt mighty and potent Kings of
<hi>England, Poland, Denmark, Swede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with all Republicks, Cities and
Corporations Chriſtian, to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and joyn in one, their ſtrengths and
powers in war againſt this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kered common Enemy of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Crowns
and Dignities.</p>
               <p>Imploring and beſeeching all ſorts of Powers and Authorities
ſpiritual and temporal, to imploy their dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and ſhew the
worthineſs of<pb n="83" facs="tcp:98077:87"/>their callings, by correction and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment
of wicked and diſſolute looſe livers, by whom God's wrath is kindled
againſt us; and to reduce them to holy Rules of Chriſtian Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, in
living juſtly, ſoberly and religiouſly, and ſo render God a true
account of Stewardſhip, and prevent the miſeries have befallen others
drowſie and ſleeping inadvertencies.</p>
               <p>Imploring and beſeeching both young and old, of all ſects
and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, godly Chriſtians religious and ſecular, beloved Fathers,
dear Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, reſpected Friends, Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and Companions, that you all,
with humble face and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, pure and ſincere hearts and hands, devout
minds, mournful voyces, and weeping eyes, condole, grieve, and lament the
miſeries, the calamities of Turkiſh captives; and call unto the Lord of
Hoſts with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, in pity to his people, to avert his anger, and not to
give them up to the perpetual rebuke of this wicked In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidel, moſt cruel
Enemy of Chriſtian Religion and Liberty; but to inſpire the mindes of
Chriſtian Kings and<pb n="84" facs="tcp:98077:88"/>Governours, with light of his holy
Spirit, to reduce them all to unity and concord, againſt this ravenous and
inſatiable Dragon; and grant o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſuch ſucceſs, that theſe
wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed captives, their Chriſtian Brethren, may be reſtored to liberty in
the worſhip and adoration of their God, our Chriſt, and onely ſerve him,
who is for ever bleſſed; that at length the Chriſtian World may be
refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and eas'd from ſuch perpetual ſlavery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>An Exhortation againſt the <hi>Turk.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have often marvelled with my ſelf, moſt mighty Monarchs,
when I conſidered theadvantages which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe Chriſtians victories
againſt the <hi>Turk;</hi> and yet in ſo many years they attempted none, or
failed. We have Jeſus Chriſt our God, who in one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly night deſtroyed
the hoſt of <hi>Senna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib;</hi> who drowned <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> who with a
maiden hand of <hi>Judith,</hi> ſtruck off the head of <hi>Holopherues;</hi>
and, to<pb n="85" facs="tcp:98077:88"/>be brief, a God, whoſe will is victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Contrary
to which, they have <hi>Mahomet,</hi> a wicked man of life and converſation;
in death yet, hanging in his Sepulchre without Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo as there
is as much difference between them, as is between an ever living Son of an ever
living God, and a putrid carkaſs of a ſon of a mortal man; that if we
diligently examine the nature of each Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, it would apear like
dead men, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors in ſtrength to living. Now in abilities of bodies,
capacities, and gifts of underſtanding, we exceed them; which are good
ſtrengths and fortifications againſt an enemy: and yet we are ſtill
defeated. Who is more hardy then the <hi>Hungarian?</hi> more ſtout and
robuſtious then the <hi>German?</hi> more quick and nimble then the
<hi>Frenchmen?</hi> more grave and ſolid than the <hi>Spaniard?</hi> more
cautelous and prudent then the <hi>Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an?</hi> more valiant and daring then
the <hi>Engliſh?</hi> forbearing other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the endowments of whoſe
mindes, are better, or at leaſt equal. All theſe abilities ſeem able
ſingly to<pb n="86" facs="tcp:98077:89"/>get a victory, or at leaſt well to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
it. Courage often without much force, generoſity of minde, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
forecaſt, ambition of honour, and policy, oft ſubdues an Enemy; yet
notwithſtanding, wretches as we are, amongſt ſo many victorious
attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, we get no victories. Then if we conſider the eaſie preparation
and great furnitures of all ſorts of arms, we ſhall appear far to exceed
the Turk. Guns of all ſorts have been our own inventions, and the divers
kinds of compleat harneſſes for horſe and foot. The Turks, Perſians
Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, naked, or half ſo, march forth to war: they have bows, we guns,
that is, fire and thunder: they have arrows, which hardly pierce and Armour; we
Cannons, which Rocks cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand: and yet now ſome
<hi>Muſſelmen</hi> have Guns and Gunners, but few, and unskilful.</p>
               <p>Now I pray, what other kinde of people uſe they moſt in
Expeditions? <hi>Scythians</hi> and <hi>Thracians,</hi> who have no
<hi>Italian</hi> or <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Spirits, onely a kinde of inhumane
fierceneſs, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and ſtolidity: to theſe are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded 
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:98077:89"/>
                  <hi>Grecians,</hi> loſt men with eaſe and lazineſs;
<hi>Aſians,</hi> corrupt with luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> no leſs in
minde then bodies, feebled; <hi>Arabians,</hi> bloodleſs, thin, and parboyl'd
with the Sun. Who could imagine ſuch kinde of Souldiery ſhould ſubdue the
great advantages and abilities of thoſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Nations? yet (be it
ſpoken with grief) our Chriſtians by theſe are overcome, and maſtered
into ſervitude, and our great Captains are forced to bear arms againſt us,
who were born and bred by Anceſtors to liberty: and in the mean ſeaſon,
the <hi>Turk</hi> laughs at us, and the <hi>Jew</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth.</p>
               <p>Now if I ſhould conſider the Laws and Inſtitutions of
Nations, we ſhall be found abundantly ſuperior in that reſpect: for, what
is more righteous and divine then the Decalogue and holy Goſpel, written by
Gods own Finger and his Spirit? what more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular then the Canon-Law? more
juſt and equal then the Civil Law? Whereas the Turks live by Direction and
Dictates of the <hi>Alcoran;</hi> a book of ſtuff as fooliſh, as full of
vanity; a<pb n="88" facs="tcp:98077:90"/>book of ſport and mirth, if pity for the
ſeduced did not allay it; though now ſpread abroad too much, and handled
amongſt Chriſtians; ſo as it may be truly feared, we ſhall learn o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
Laws, or ſhortly looſe our own, and turn Turks in our minds and
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probations, ſooner then in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to their Dominion. VVhat is then
the cauſe, having ſo many Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives of hopeful War, we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
beaten? why are our Enſigns adorn'd with Crucifixes, fearful for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly to
Infidels and Devils, now trampled on and ſlighted? I ſhall tell you in few
words, and truth. We have a God moſt great, moſt good; but alienated from
us ſo far, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Prophets ſaying, <hi>We ſcarce are to
be named his people:</hi> for why ſhould Chriſt remain with us, whom we
have rent and corn in far more pieces then the Souldiers did his Garment, by
our hideous Sects, Schiſms and Hereſies? Beſides his Name, what of him is
deap unto us? The very Plow-man theſe times is impudent and factious, the
Citizen fraudulent and avaritious, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate<pb n="89" facs="tcp:98077:90"/>ſeeks
retributions and rewards, the Nobility is riotous and lazy, the Gentry
contentious and proud; the Souldier, beyond his pay and ſpoile, craves
nothing from the War; let Scepters fall as they will, he is no leſs grievous
to friends and companions, then Enemies. Church-men, beſides pomp
Eccleſiaſtical, have little of the Church; not ſanctity, not piety, and
ſome not fitting erudition; ſeeking their own, not Chriſts advancement;
that we may ſay with the Prophet, <hi>All have declin'd the ways of God, and
are unprofitable; there's none that doth good, not even one.</hi> Why ſhould
we marvel then that Chriſt is not our Friend? We therefore go to war without
a God, and what is more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitous, with God our adverſery: We carry Bibles
and Crucifixes with us, but the crucified by his favour converſeth with our
enemies; our Actions therefore periſh, and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd in loſſes. And
when one Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fights againſt the Turk, another is employ'd in civil wars,
calling to his aid Pagans, Schiſmaticks or He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, more eagerly to
oppoſe<pb n="90" facs="tcp:98077:91"/>Chriſt; others tend their home-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, to
indulge themſelves in eaſe and voluptuouſneſs. The ſouldier ſets
not forth for Chriſt, but money; which failing, ſoon deſerts the field,
and turns home back again. What have we then from thoſe rich Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes and
Eulogies of <hi>Germany, France, England, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> when
the ſouldier neglects both God and Honour, and goes to war as to market, a
brothel-houſe, or ſtews, to exerciſe all rapine, ſpoile, and
lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? We have good Laws, but evil manners; good furniture of Arms, but
wicked diſpoſitions: it is our glory to fight among our ſelves; and if we
prove coward to enemies, there follows little ſhame or puniſhment. When do
we ſee a Souldier quitting colours or disbanding, ſeverely hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? which
crimes were anciently capital; and whole Legions have been decimated and tyth'd
for leſs offences. We therefore march with men few in numbers, and thoſe
cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt in manners, againſt millions of men well diſciplin'd; for Turks
leave their vices in their houſes, from<pb n="91" facs="tcp:98077:91"/>whence we carry
ours. In their Pavili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Tents, no deliciouſneſs; Arms onely, and
neceſſary proviſions: in Chriſtians, all forts of Table-deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates,
luxury and riotouſneſs; and commonly, as many light laſcivious Women, as
Men. What wonder then if they conquer who are preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by ſobriety,
parſimony, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, fidelity and obedience? Let them periſh then, who
loſe a field to get a prey; who are oftner found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Whores, and
drunk, then in good actions: but 'tis the fault and errour of Superiours, when
Subjects are not kept in due obſervance; which if Chriſtians were, we could
not be inferiour to Turks. And yet a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fault, behold, Princes
themſelves, while they contend in mutual quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, are cauſes why they
cannot mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter equal forces againſt the Turk: for whilſt they fight and
combate for ſome little Town or other, after grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſtrife,
conflictation and exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of men and treaſure, they grow weak,
impoveriſhed and heartleſs. What brave Actions might thoſe ſtreams of
Chriſtian blood have done,<pb n="92" facs="tcp:98077:92"/>which civil wars moſt
impiouſly have drawn out, emptied, and dried up? But 'tis too late to mourn
in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints: <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Affrica</hi> are loſt;
<hi>Greece,</hi> extinguiſhed; <hi>Hungary,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately ſick;
<hi>Illyria</hi> and <hi>Sclavonia,</hi> joyned to the Turk;
<hi>Auſtria,</hi> much enfeebled; and this Plague much threatens
<hi>Germany,</hi> and Chriſtianity univerſal; and that ſo far, that no
great Prince or Monarch ought to be ſecure, or think himſelf ſo free, but
that he may be forced to deſend his own, without invaſion of his
neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Territories, whether it pleaſe or not; unleſs they will become,
of Princes, Servants; of Free-men, Slaves, detained in perpetual chains, or
flain and murthered, that their Subjects may want Captains and good
Leaders.</p>
               <p>Now, moſt mighty Monarchs and high Governors, for Gods
cauſe, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh from amongſt you all diſcord and ambitious tyrannies,
(which are the Devils inſtruments to maintain oppreſſions and impieties,
thereby to prolong Gods wrath upon you) and reſtore to each Proprietor his
due<pb n="93" facs="tcp:98077:92"/>rights and priviledges; and then, as Rivers having free
courſe, haſte all ſmoothly to the Sea, and make one mighty body; ſo
your ſtrengths uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the bond of peace, would ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, aſtoniſh
and drown this great Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Turk. Which bleſſing on ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded knees I humbly
pray for, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend unto the God of Peace. And being reconcil'd among your
ſelves, if you would ſay as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid to <hi>Joſhua,
Chuſe you a man, and go and fight with Amelek;</hi> if you would reduce your
ſelves to this peace and concord, (which is onely hopeful) and put your
helping hands and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers toward ſo greatly honourable, ſo bleſſed,
ſo neceſſary and profitable a War againſt the Turk; who can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine,
but that ye ſhould at leaſt equal the number of his Souldiery, if not far
exceed them? He is now ſwell'd up to the very heighth of Tyranny, and hath
there remained ſo for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers years, as if expecting, as if wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an
Attempt. All full Seas have their ebbings, all ripe fruits are quickly ſhaken
down; there wants no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to this general and glorious<pb n="94" facs="tcp:98077:93"/>work
of Chriſtian Princes, but Gods bleſſing, unanimity, and an heroick
courage, brave and maſculine. For the Emperour can with eaſineſs raiſe,
arm and muſter 50000 horſe, and 100000 foot; the like may hopeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be
expected from <hi>France,</hi> from <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy:</hi> the yet
remaining parts of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Illyria,</hi> with the Provinces
under the King of <hi>Romans,</hi> will raiſe and maintain 60000. Theſe
Chriſtian forces may make 400000 horſe and foot, beſides the Maritime
great aſſiſtances of <hi>England, Denmark,</hi> united Provinces,
<hi>Venetians, Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals</hi> and <hi>Swedes,</hi> and all other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
Commonwealths, who, if once unanimous, and freed from jealouſies and petty,
wretched, wilful, home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentions, the Turkiſh power could no more
reſiſt ye, then <hi>Darius, Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander; Xerxes, Themiſtocles;</hi> or
<hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochus, Judas Macchabeus:</hi> and having gotten but one Victory, and
once paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Danube</hi> towards <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> God
being pleaſed, and our lives amended, theſe enemies of our faith would
eaſily be trodden down. All <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Thrace</hi> (where yet
great<pb n="95" facs="tcp:98077:93"/>part retain the Law of Chriſt) expect with
greedineſs the Chriſtian Sword, and readily would revolt upon ſuch
occaſion, and manful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſault and fight againſt thoſe Lords and
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that have ſo cruelly afflicted them: which circumſtance alone,
would much haſten, if not perfect a ſpeedy victory.</p>
               <p>I would to God, and wiſh heartily, moſt Chriſtian
Monarchs, That your civil, fruitleſs, home-contentions, would permit and
ſuffer you ſeriouſly to conſider, and calmly to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine theſe
offered motions; you then would finde all mens wills and arms concur with
yours; no age, no ſex, no conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men would leave your Enſigns: Each
<hi>Turk</hi> would have his Executioner at home, his Traytor in his Tent, and
fugitive in the Field. All Chriſtians amongſt them have contemptuous
opinions of their arms, and know them onely ſitted for light Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes
and Pickerings; who, if their noiſe, like ſhoals of clamouring Rocks,
affright you not, they flee. And whenſoever it ſhall pleaſe God to root
out from amongſt us theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Enemies of his faith, and ſend them
to their old lurking holes, and caves and corners in <hi>Bythinia,</hi> by the
Chriſtian Sword (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to ſome of their own Prophecies) or elſe to
reduce them to the boſome of our Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick<pb n="96" facs="tcp:98077:94"/>Church, no man
can donbt, but in ſhort time the Emperor will be ſeated in his chair at
<hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and inveſted in his Imperial Roman Territories;
The King of <hi>Romans</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhed, and recover <hi>Hungary,</hi>
and <hi>Thrace; France,</hi> leſſer <hi>Aſia; England,</hi> part of
<hi>Egypt; Spain,</hi> part of <hi>Africa; Italy,</hi> all Shores and Banks of
the Mediterranean Seas; and laſt, the Pope, as a great Paſtor of the
Chriſtian Church, will be extol'd and magnifi'd for ſuch an union.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the apprehenſions of all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an captives
under the Turkiſh Tribute, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Turks themſelves, who have-knowledge
and long acquaintance in military affairs. And this my ſelf have learned by
thirteen yeers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, The <hi>Turk</hi> is valiant againſt a flying,
and flying againſt a valiant Enemy; when there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he by nature is fugitive,
impiety flyes without purſuit. Let God ariſe and ſcatter all his Enemies:
let thoſe that hate his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, avoid his preſence: let them like
ſmoak vaniſh, and melt like wax againſt the fire: ſo may all Infidels
periſh, before the face of God and his holy Church, that there may be but one
Flock, and one Paſtor, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous. Which grant, Oh ever
bleſſed Trinity and Unity, God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy
Ghoſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:98077:94"/>
               <head>The Seraglio of the women and Sulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas of the Great
SIGNOR.</head>
               <p>BEfore I diſmiſs this Subject, to ſatiſſie ſome
Curioſities con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Emperours pleaſures, in which he ſatiates
himſelf with variety, converſing with his <hi>Mutes</hi> and
<hi>Buffones</hi> (for that it is not lawful for any body but the Vizier
Baſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and ſome few others
to ſpeak to him) in the ſame fignes and geſtures, and now and then
riding, and ſhooting &amp; caſting a heavy Iron Mace, all which he is
taught to do with great exactneſs; I will tranſiently ſpeak of that, then
which nothing is more ſecret and reſerved <hi>viz.</hi> His Companying with
women, the beautifulleſt thoſe parts of the world afford, the greateſt
excellency and perfection whereof is reputed to conſiſt in great and broad
eyes; the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of women ſo featured, being made a part of their
Paradiſe in the world to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:98077:95"/>They which are within the third gate, called
the Kings gate, are about two thouſand perſons, men and women; whereof the
women (old and young one with another; what with the Kings Concubines, Old
women, and women Servants) may be about eleven or twelve hundred. Now thoſe
which are kept up for their beauties, are all young Virgins, taken and
ſtollen from forraign Nations; who after they have been inſtructed in good
behavior, and can play upon Inſtruments, ſing, dance, and ſew
curiouſly; they are given to the <hi>Grand Signor</hi> as preſents of great
value: and the number of theſe encreaſeth daily, as they are ſent and
preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the <hi>Tartars,</hi> by the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaws,</hi> and other
great men, to the King and Queen. They do likewiſe ſometimes decreaſe,
accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the <hi>Grand Signor</hi> ſhall think fit. For upon divers
occaſions and accidents, he cauſeth many<pb n="99" facs="tcp:98077:95"/>of them to be
turned out of this <hi>Seraglio,</hi> and to be ſent into the old
<hi>Seraglio:</hi> which is alſo a very goodly and ſpacious place, of which
hereafter I ſhall take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to make mention. 
<note place="margin">Virgins made Turks and how.</note>Theſe
Virgins immediately after their coming into the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> are made
<hi>Turks;</hi> which is done by uſing this Ceremony onely; to hold up their
forefinger and ſay theſe words; <hi>law illawheh illaw Allawh, Muhammed
reſoul Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawh.</hi> That is, there is no God but God alone, and
<hi>Mahomet</hi> is the meſſenger of God. 
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Kahiyah Cadun,</hi> the mother of the
maids.</note>As they are in age and diſpoſition (being proved and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
by an old woman called <hi>Kahiyah Cadun,</hi> that is, as we ſay, the Mother
of the Maids) ſo they are placed in a room with the others of the ſame age,
ſpirit, and inclination, to dwell and live together.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Their manner of life.</note>Now in the womens
lodgings, they live juſt as Nuns do in great <pb n="100" facs="tcp:98077:96"/>Nunneries,
for theſe Virgins have very large rooms to live in: and their Bed-Chambers
will hold al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a hundred of them a piece. They ſleep upon
<hi>Sofaes,</hi> which are built longwiſe on both ſides of the room, and a
large ſpace left in the midſt to go to and fro about their
buſineſs.</p>
               <p>Their Beds are very courſe and hard (for the Turks neither
uſe Feather-beds, nor Corded Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteads) and by every ten Virgins there
lies an old woman and all the night long there are many lamps burning, ſo
that one may ſee plainly throughout the whole room: which doth both keep the
wenches from wantonneſs, and ſerve upon any occaſion which may happen in
the night. Near unto the ſaid Bed-chambers they have their <hi>Bagnos</hi>
for their all times: with many uſe at Fountains, out of which they are
ſerved with water, and above<pb n="101" facs="tcp:98077:96"/>their Chambers there are
divers rooms, where they ſit and ſew: and there they keep their Books, and
Cheſts, in which they lay up their apparel.</p>
               <p>They feed by whole <hi>Camara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daes,</hi> and are ſerved and
waited upon by other women: nor do they want any thing whatſoever, that is
neceſſary for them.</p>
               <p>There are other places likewiſe for them, where they go to
School, to learn to ſpeak and read (if they will) the Turkiſh tongue, to
ſew alſo, and to play on divers Inſtruments, ſo they ſpend the day
with their Miſtreſſes, who are all ancient women: ſome hours
notwithſtanding being allowed them for their recreation, to walk in their
gardens, and uſe ſuch ſports as they familiarly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe themſelves
withal.</p>
               <p>The King doth not at all fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent or ſee theſe Virgins,
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be at that inſtant when they are firſt preſented unto him;
or elſe<pb n="102" facs="tcp:98077:97"/>in caſe that he deſire one of them for his
Bed-fellow, or to make him ſome paſtime with muſick or other ſports:
wherfore when he is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for a freſh Mate, he gives no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to the
<hi>Kahiya Cadun</hi> of his purpoſe; who immediately beſtirs her ſelf
like a crafty Baud, and chuſeth out ſuch as ſhe judgeth to be moſt
amiable, and faireſt of all; and having placed them in good order in a room,
in two ranks, like ſo many pictures, half on the one ſidr, and half on the
other, 
<note place="margin">The Kings eoming to them.</note>ſhe
forthwith brings in the King, who walking four or five times in the midſt of
them, and having viewed them well, taketh good notice within himſelf of her
that he beſt liketh, but ſays nothing; onely as he goeth out again, he
throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a handkercheif into that Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins hand; by which token ſhe knoweth
that ſhe is to lie with him that night: ſo ſhe being (queſtionleſs)
exceeding joyful to become the object of ſo great a<pb n="103" facs="tcp:98077:97"/>fortune, in being choſen outfrom among ſo many, to enjoy the
ſociety of an Emperour, hath all the art that poſſible may be, ſhown
upon her by the <hi>Cadun,</hi> in atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, painting, and perfuming her; and
at night ſhe is brought to ſleep with the <hi>Grand Signor</hi> in the
womans lodgings, where there are Chambers ſet apart for that buſineſs
onely. And being in bed together, they have two great wax lights burning by
them all night; one at the beds feet, and the other by the door: beſides
there are appointed (by the <hi>Cadun</hi>) divers old Black-more women, to
watch by turns that night in the Chamber, by two at a time; one of them to
ſit by the light at the beds feet, and the other by the door, and when they
will they change, and other two ſupply their rooms, without making the
leaſt noiſe imaginable, ſo that the King is not any whit diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.
Now in the morning when<pb n="104" facs="tcp:98077:98"/>his Highneſs riſeth (for he
riſeth firſt) he changeth all his apparel from top to toe, leaving thoſe
w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he wore, to her that he lay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and all the money that was in his
pockets, were it never ſo much; and ſo departeth to his own lodgings; from
whence alſo he ſendeth her immediately a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of jewels, money, and
veſts, of great value, agreeable to the ſatisfaction and content which he
received from her that night. In the ſame manner he deals with all ſuch as
he maketh uſe of in that kind; but with ſome he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth longer then
with other ſome, and enlargeth his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, far more towards ſome then
others; according as his humour, and affection to them, encreaſeth, by their
fulfilling his luſtful deſires.</p>
               <p>And if ſo fall out, that any one of them doth conceive by him,
and bring forth his firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten child; then ſhe is called by 
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:98077:98"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sultna</hi> Queen.</note> the name
of <hi>Sultana,</hi> Queen: and if it be a Son, ſhe is confirmed and
eſtabliſhed by great feaſts, and ſolemnities; and forth with hath a
dwelling asſigned unto her apart, of many ſtately rooms well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed;
and many ſervants to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon her.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Her al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance.</note>The King likewiſe
alloweth her a large revenue, that ſhe may give away, and ſpend at her
pleaſure, in whatſoever ſhe may have occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and all they of the
<hi>Seraglio</hi> muſt, and do acknowledge her for Queen, ſhewing all the
duty and reſpect that may be, both to her ſelf, and to them that belong
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Other <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tana's</hi>
                  </note>The other
women (howſoever they bring forth iſſue) are not called Queens; yet they
are called <hi>Sultana's,</hi> becauſe they have had carnal commerce with the
King: and ſhe onely is called Queen, which is the Mother of the firſt
begotten ſon, heir to the Empire; the which <hi>Sultanas,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:98077:99"/>frequented by the King at his pleaſure, have alſo this
preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; to be immediately remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the common ſort, and to live in
rooms apart, exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well ſerved and attended; and have no want either of
money, or apparel, in conformity to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</p>
               <p>All theſe <hi>Sultanaes</hi> do reſort to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether very
familiarly, when they pleaſe; but not without great diſſimulation, and
inward ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice; fearing leſt the one ſhould be better beloved of the
<hi>Grand Signor</hi> then the other; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this their
jealouſie, they (in outward ſhew) uſe all kind of courteſie one towards
another.</p>
               <p>They never ſtir out of the <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glio</hi> but in company
of the King himſelf, who often times carry; either all, or moſt of them
abroad by water, to his other <hi>Seraglios</hi> of pleaſure: and in thoſe
ways through which they paſs, to go<pb n="107" facs="tcp:98077:99"/>to and fro from their
<hi>Kaiks,</hi> there is Canvas pitched up on both ſides, and none may come
near them but black <hi>Eunuches,</hi> till they be ſetled, and covered
cloſe in the room, at the ſtern of the <hi>Kaik;</hi> and then go in the
<hi>Bargemen;</hi> ſo that in fine they are never ſeen by any men, but by
the <hi>Grand Signor</hi> only, and the <hi>Eunuchs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Kings Daughters, Siſters, and Aunts, have their lodgings
alſo in the ſame <hi>Seraglio;</hi> being royally ſerved, and very
ſumptuouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled, and live together by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in continual
pleaſures; until ſuch time as at their requeſt the King ſhall be
pleaſed to give them in marriage: and then they come forth of that
<hi>Seraglio,</hi> and carry each of them along with them a cheſt which the
<hi>Grand Signor</hi> gives them, full of rich apparel, jewels, and money; to
the value of (at the leaſt) thirty thouſand pounds ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a cheſt;
and that is (as we call it) their portion.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:98077:100"/>
               <p>There are many other things which are worthy a Diſcourſe,
and Relation in this Magnificent Court and family of the <hi>Grand Signor,</hi>
but being confined by time to this Volume, they muſt awayt a fairer
opportunity of Publication.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98077:100"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
